<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hagio-mimesis The imitation of the saints : opened in some practical meditations upon the death of Mrs. Anne Browne, late wife of Mr. Peter Browne of Hammersmith / by Thomas Case ...</title>
            <author>Case, Thomas, 1598-1682.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35574</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C822</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37528</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16966911</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16966911</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105540</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35574)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105540)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1611:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hagio-mimesis The imitation of the saints : opened in some practical meditations upon the death of Mrs. Anne Browne, late wife of Mr. Peter Browne of Hammersmith / by Thomas Case ...</title>
                  <author>Case, Thomas, 1598-1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First 2 words of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews VI, 12 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105540:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>'ΑΓΙΩ-ΜΙΜΕΣΙΣ. THE IMITATION Of the SAINTS. Opened in ſome Practical Meditations Upon the death of Mrs. ANNE BROWNE, late Wife of Mr. PETER BROWNE of <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſmith.</hi> By <hi>Thomas Caſe, M. A.</hi> ſometimes Student of <hi>Chriſt-Church, Oxon.</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Heb. 13.7.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> 1666.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:105540:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105540:2"/>
            <head>To his honoured Friend, and Son in-law, Mr. <hi>Peter Browne</hi> of <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſmith.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Grace, Mercy,</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NOt to <hi>revive</hi> your ſorrow for the loſs of your precious <hi>Yoke-Fellow,</hi> but to <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate</hi> and <hi>regulate</hi> it, do theſe Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons offer themſelves to your view: <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians</hi> ſay, that if <hi>rheum</hi> be <hi>ſweetned,</hi> it cannot hurt the <hi>lungs;</hi> ſure I am, if <hi>grief</hi> be <hi>ſweetned</hi> and <hi>ſanctified,</hi> it cannot hurt the <hi>heart;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.10</note> 
               <hi>Worldly ſorrow</hi> indeed may <hi>cauſe death,</hi> but <hi>godly ſorrow</hi> tendeth to <hi>ſalvation;</hi> that your ſorrow may be ſuch, let me com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the reading of theſe Papers to <hi>you,</hi> and do you, (by holy prayer) commend them to God. Neither <hi>grief</hi> nor <hi>mirth, (ſimply in themſelves)</hi> are <hi>ſinful</hi> and <hi>hurtful,</hi> but as the <hi>Object</hi> or degree determines them.</p>
            <p>Your Wife (I know) while ſhe lived,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.16.</note> was <hi>the deſire of your eyes;</hi> ſo pleaſant an Object, that I cannot but preſume her very Picture now ſhe is dead, will be a moſt <hi>acceptable Preſent;</hi> which though not drawn by a curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Penſil, yet (I dare be bold to ſay) it
<pb facs="tcp:105540:3"/>is ſo <hi>like her</hi> that whoſoever knew her, will know whoſe Picture it is, at the <hi>firſt-ſight;</hi> I am ſure the Painter hath not flattered Her. It is a <hi>life-Picture</hi> (as Artiſts call them) taken <hi>from her face,</hi> and not by <hi>Copy.</hi> A <hi>life-Picture indeed;</hi> deſcribing not the outward <hi>Effigies</hi> of her <hi>face</hi> but the inward <hi>Pourtraiture</hi> of her <hi>mind,</hi> all fair and beautiful: I commend it to your <hi>ſelf,</hi> and your <hi>Friends;</hi> not to hang on your <hi>Walls,</hi> but to <hi>wear in your boſom.</hi> If the fight of it ſhould occaſion your tears, I ſhall not repent, becauſe by the <hi>ſadneſs of the Countenance</hi> the heart is made <hi>better,</hi> and <hi>ſorrow</hi> will flow in the right <hi>Channel,</hi> not the <hi>abſence of her perſon,</hi> ſo much as the <hi>want of her graces.</hi> Give me leave, by that intereſt ſhe gave me in you, to enjoyn you, both the <hi>ſerious,</hi> and the <hi>frequent</hi> review of this <hi>piece;</hi> and if you joyn prayer with your contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it will make you <hi>inſenſibly to paſs into her likeneſs;</hi> for which end you will find this <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription</hi> engraven round about her <hi>Effigies, Whoſe faith follow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This do, <hi>ſincerely, vigorouſly,</hi> and <hi>perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly,</hi> and I dare aſſure you, your <hi>loſs</hi> will be your <hi>gain;</hi> which is and ſhall be the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your affectionate Friend and Father in-Law, <hi>Tho. Caſe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:105540:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>'TWas extreamly obliging that you honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me with the peruſal of your <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giomimeſis,</hi> (the occaſion was ſad, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement good) where the nature and ground of the Imitation of Saints, is diſtinctly opened, and rarely Illuſtrated by an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent example; when that <hi>digitus ferro-luteus</hi> ſaw the fatal houre approaching, he cryed out,<note place="margin">Dan. <hi>2.42</hi> Sueton in v. Ner.</note> 
               <hi>ut ſe aliquis ad mortem capeſſendam exemplo juvaret,</hi> that ſome one would die by him, that he might learn to die by the example; and this was like him, whoſe name was <hi>vir ſanguinum,</hi> a man of blood: But that brave perſon, that great Saint your treatiſe refers to, hath by the incomparable inſtance of her gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious behaviour, taught us all, how to die, and now to live too, which is the firſt and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt leſſon. <hi>Benè vixiſſe, magnum eſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jerome.</note> I judge
<pb facs="tcp:105540:4"/>the ſame Anointing which took her up to the Galleries of Love, faſhioning her inſenſibly into ſo curious a Preſident, hath diſcloſed to you this ſecret,<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 13 21.</note> of giving life by dead bones, preſerving Religion from mortality, gathering flowers from the Coffin, Embalming Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and finding out advantages in the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Providences. Good <hi>Sir</hi> let me once more deſire you to publiſh your Meditations on this ſubject, and the rather, becauſe we have had the fire of the laſt day, lately repreſented to us in a dreadful figure, happily you may now at length provoke the preſent evill world to Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation,<note place="margin">Surius in vit.</note> and ſave ſome. <hi>Jerome</hi> eſpouſed the example of <hi>Hilarion.</hi> Who knows in what me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods God will pleaſe to diſcover himſelf to poor ſinners? Will any ſay, (they knew not <hi>Hammer-Smith</hi>) you dipped your Pen too much in love, when you drew the fair Character of an endeared Child? Regard it not, <hi>aequo ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo audienda ſunt imperitorum convitia,<note place="margin">Sen. ep. <hi>76.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; ad honeſta vadenti contemnendus eſt iſte contemptus.</hi> The Inhabitants of the Earth are ſo much below the cloud of witneſſes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. Mop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyed.</note> that being <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>Tender eyed, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net ſee the glory wrap't up in it; Let the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſay in ſcorn to <hi>Eliſha,</hi> go up, go up (meaning as <hi>Elias</hi> did) 'tis enough for him to inherit his Maſters ſpirit,<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.23.</note> and to ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:105540:4"/>the Aſcendent in Divine Grace. Some years ſince the merciful Providence of God gave me a Summers reſt in the houſe of that admirable Perſon (which I ever after found to be one of the hundred built upon the Land of Promiſe) much was I there alſo in her laſt ſickneſs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.29.</note> and ſtill I obſerved Wiſdom and Holineſs, Gravity and Meekneſs,<note place="margin">Iſocr. He. Lau. Num. <hi>14.24.</hi>
                  </note> tempered in her to an unparallel'd ſweetneſs. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. A bleſt <hi>Pandora,</hi> a highly favoured <hi>Enthumia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In. Solin. Polyhist. c. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> one that had the Other ſpirit, the <hi>Even</hi> ſpirit, <hi>eodem vultus teno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, etiam adverſis interpellantibus perſtitit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pomp. Mel. <hi>3.</hi> de orbis ſitu.</note> as was ſaid of <hi>Socrates.</hi> The pure ſpirit came down upon her, rather <hi>tanquam Columba,</hi> then <hi>inſtar ignis;</hi> hers was that Dove-like, Agnine ſpirit; <hi>pro eloquio nutus erat,</hi> with what wonderful regard did ſhe walk? <hi>Tota pulcra,</hi> all fair, and ever fair, ſhining with holineſs when deſcended from the Mount; her Manna ſeemed to breed no Worm; Chriſt dwelt in her with a conſtant lovelineſs, and was fairer in her, then in ten thouſands! She did excel to a wonder in the eſteem of all that converſed with her. But now ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fallen, ſhe is fallen, and gone down to the Chambers of the Dead. <hi>A tutto vi è rime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:105540:5"/>fuor che alla morte.</hi> Haſten therfore to us your <hi>Hagiomimeſis,</hi> that the fall of the righteous may be the Salvation of the world,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.11.</note> which is the hearts deſire, and prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Dear SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your Servant in our Lord, <hi>William Woodward.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>Octob. 10. 1666.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105540:5"/>
            <head>THE IMITATION Of the SAINTS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Heb. 6.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But followers of them who through faith and patience, inherit the promiſes.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Apoſtle having ſet before the believing <hi>Hebrews,</hi> a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful inſtance of <hi>the ſin,</hi> and <hi>danger of Apoſtacy,</hi> from verſe the 4th to verſe the 8th (for the awakening of them out of their <hi>ſecurity,</hi> to a timely <hi>prevention</hi> of both) that he might not oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion prejudice and offence in their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms, as if he had judged them to be A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtates,</p>
            <p>He doth two things:</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:105540:6"/>
            <p n="1">1. He ſweetly inſinuates <hi>a better opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them,</hi> verſe 9.10. <hi>But beloved, we are perſwaded b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tter things of you,</hi> and the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of which p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ſion, he gives you verſe 10th <hi>for God is not unrighteous co for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abour of love,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Yet. That they may not think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves altogether <hi>unconcerned</hi> in this cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he admoniſheth them to take heed of <hi>ſluggiſhneſs and ſecurity</hi> (on the one ſide) which are the uſuall <hi>ſnare</hi> and <hi>precipice</hi> to Apoſtacy, That ye <hi>be not ſlothfull;</hi> And then he incites them to a <hi>vigorous dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> in their Chriſtian profeſſion (on the other ſide) the <hi>way</hi> and <hi>means</hi> which God hath ſanctified for the attaining of <hi>perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> and <hi>aſſurance,</hi> Verſe 11th. <hi>We de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that every one of you do ſhew the ſame diligence to the full aſſurance of hope unto the end.</hi> The <hi>ſame, i. e.</hi> the <hi>ſame,</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned verſe 10th <hi>Your work and labour of love:</hi> q. d. <hi>That which ſome of you have</hi> given abundant teſtimony of, <hi>I deſire eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of you</hi> may give alſo; leſt there ſhould be any that may poſſibly fall ſhort, and prove Apoſtate amongſt you.</p>
            <p>Or the <hi>ſame, i. e.</hi> which <hi>you your ſelves</hi> (ſpeaking to the ſame individuals) have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that <hi>ye</hi> grow not <hi>remiſs</hi> and <hi>negligent</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:105540:6"/>in your love and zeal; for then if you that have been formerly diligent and active, ſhall cool, and grow negligent, not only your former diligence will be a teſtimony againſt you; but the abatement and decay of your love and zeal, may expoſe you to the ſin and danger of <hi>Apoſtacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now both theſe he doth, by propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Pattern</hi> of the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Worthies</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> to their pious <hi>Conſideration</hi> and <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation.</hi> Some of whom were yet <hi>alive,</hi> whom he propoſeth as Preſidents to the reſt among them: Yea, he propoſeth <hi>themſelves</hi> to <hi>themſelves;</hi> their <hi>former zeal,</hi> to prevent their <hi>future luke-warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others here commended, were ſuch of the Primitive <hi>Heroes,</hi> who had long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, finiſhed their courſe and obtained the Crown:<note n="*" place="margin">Ego de patribus jam in coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis agere hoc loco Apostolum non dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, <hi>Bez.</hi> in loc.</note> As <hi>Abraham,</hi> mentioned in the verſes following my Text; and <hi>others,</hi> of thoſe famous Lights of the World, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in the word <hi>them</hi> (in the Text) <hi>Them</hi> who through faith and patience in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the promiſes. Theſe alſo the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth commend as ſtanding exemplars for the believing <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and (in them) for all other Chriſtians, profeſſing the Name and faith of Jeſus Chriſt, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:105540:7"/>
            <p>Now, to be <hi>followers of the Saints,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nothing elſe but <hi>vigorouſly</hi> and <hi>conſtantly</hi> to endeavor to <hi>Imitate</hi> them in their <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and <hi>gracious converſations:</hi> to uſe all diligence to be <hi>ſuch</hi> as they were; and to do as they did, in our times and places.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That you be followers of them, who through faith and patience,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>We may look upon the words under a twofold aſpect.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Poſitive.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Relative.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Poſitive,</hi> as expreſſing, and preſſing a <hi>Duty neceſſary,</hi> for all Chriſtians to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and that is a <hi>diligent imitation of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Relative,</hi> as implying a <hi>Soveraign re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy,</hi> to prevent the <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>danger</hi> of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy.</p>
            <p>Take them in their <hi>Poſitive aſpect,</hi> and ſo they preſent us with this Doctrinal Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. <hi>It is the duty of Chriſtians to be followers of the Saints of God, who have been, or are, excellent in their Generations;</hi> Or,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Graces of the Saints, whether alive or dead, they are Patterns ſet forth for our Imitation</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take the words in their <hi>Relative</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, and ſo they afford us this,</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:105540:7"/>
            <p>Obſervation, <hi>ſc. That a diligent imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Saints of God in their graces and vertues, is a ſpecial Preſervative and Antidote againſt Apoſtacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the firſt of theſe I intend to inſiſt upon; the other will be of uſe, in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of this.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>It is the duty of Christians to be followers of the Saints of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Noun</hi> (here,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>1 Cor. 11.1 <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>Heb. 13.7. <hi>Called.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as elſewhere) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>followers,</hi> is derived from the ſame verb which is uſed, <hi>ch.</hi> 13.7. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. which ſignifies to <hi>work according to pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern;</hi> a metaphor borrowed from <hi>Stage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playes,</hi> where the <hi>Actors</hi> ſtudy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly, and to the life, to expreſs the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures and diſpoſitions of the perſons whom they repreſent; or elſe from <hi>Apes,</hi> who do naturally love to <hi>imitate</hi> the actions and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures of men. Thus the Apoſtle calls Chriſtians to an exact and unfeigned imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Saints of God, whether <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted</hi> and in Heaven, or yet ſurviving in the Land of the living.</p>
            <p>This holy Imitation is frequently <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded</hi> in Scripture, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11. 1. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:105540:8"/>
            <p>And for this, others are <hi>comended,</hi> as 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.14. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the opening of the Doctrine, I ſhall ſhew you,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Why? The Saints are to be i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitated.</item>
               <item>2. Wherein The Saints are to be i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitated.</item>
               <item>3. How The Saints are to be i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitated.</item>
               <item>4. We ſhall improve it for our uſe and practice.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why? Now the <hi>Grounds</hi> and <hi>Reaſons</hi> of the point, are ſuch as theſe following.<note place="margin" type="runSum">1 <hi>Ground.</hi> Gods end in giving ſuch pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerns.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This was a <hi>principal end or deſign which God had in beſtowing ſuch choice and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous qualifications upon the Saints</hi> in the world, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcil.</hi>) that they might ſerve as <hi>patterns</hi> for the <hi>imitation of others,</hi> who either live with them, or come after them. Hence they are called <hi>lights, Phil.</hi> 2.15, 16.</p>
            <p>They be like the <hi>Pharo</hi>'s, or fires upon the Sea-coaſts, to ſhew paſſengers their way in the dark night, that they may not ſuffer ſhipwrack. They are looking-glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, by which the Saints ſhould dreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. God did not beſtow <hi>graces</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies</hi> upon them, meerly for their own
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105540:8"/>ſakes, for the adorning of their own ſouls, and to qualifie them for their future <hi>Glory;</hi> (though that was one gracious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſign he had upon them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5 5. <hi>Col.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.12.) but that by <hi>their light,</hi> they m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m <hi>ſhew o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> the way, <hi>holding forth the word of life;</hi> and by their <hi>heat</hi> they might <hi>warm</hi> others, and by their <hi>zeal provok many,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.2. <hi>your zeal hath provoked ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</hi> Therefore ſaith our Lord,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.51.</note> 
               <hi>let your light ſhine,</hi> &amp;c. No man <hi>lighteth a candle to put it under a bed, or under a buſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el, but on a candleſtick, that it may give light unto all that are in the houſe.</hi> Therefore as the Saints themſelves ſin againſt Gods deſign (in giving them ſuch excellent <hi>ſhining graces</hi>) <hi>when they do withhold their light</hi> and <hi>influence,</hi> by putting them under the bed of <hi>pleaſure,</hi> or the buſhel of <hi>profit.</hi> So <hi>Standers-by,</hi> ſin againſt the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ends and purpoſes of Gods love in the graces of his Saints, when they do not <hi>fruitfully improve them for their own imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They take the grace of God in <hi>vain,</hi> in his Saints; and ſlight and neglect the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed helpes which God hath afforded them in their paſſage to heaven; they regard not Gods <hi>love</hi> and <hi>care</hi> in ſetting up ſuch
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105540:9"/>lights in the world: whereas they ſhould admire God in his Saints, as <hi>David</hi> did in the workmanſhip of the Creation, and cry out in that admiration,<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Lord, what is man that thou art ſo mindfull of him!</hi> they ſhould <hi>Praiſe and glorifie God, which gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth ſuch gifts and graces unto men.</hi> And by daily comparing themſelves with theſe Patterns, ſtrive to correct their errors, and to come up to further degrees of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and perfection.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To be ſure this was one great Reaſon,<note place="margin" type="runSum">2 <hi>Ground.</hi> Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiceing ſiaung the lives of the Saints to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded.</note> why God <hi>took ſuch order</hi> by the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Holy Ghoſt, to have the <hi>lives</hi> and <hi>Graces</hi> of the Saints, ſo <hi>exactly Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred in the Scriptures,</hi> and kept upon <hi>publick record;</hi> That they might be for <hi>Patterns</hi> and <hi>Preſidents</hi> to future Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. So <hi>Octavius Auguſtus</hi> erected the Statues of the <hi>Roman Hero's, triumphali effigie.</hi> That <hi>illorum veluti ad exemplar, &amp; Ipſe dum viveret, &amp; in ſequentium aetatum principes exigerentur à Civibus. Rom.</hi> 15.4.<note place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoever things were written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foretime, were written for our learning, that we through patience and comfort of the Scriptures, might have hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105540:9"/>
            <p>Even the <hi>ſins</hi> and <hi>failings</hi> of the Saints are recorded in Scripture upon this very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 106, 11. to be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>enſamples,</hi> not indeed for our <hi>imitation,</hi> but for our <hi>caution:</hi> They be our <hi>Take-heeds,</hi> not our <hi>Patterns;</hi> to the intent we ſhould not <hi>luſt</hi> after evill things, as they alſo luſted, <hi>v.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>But now their <hi>Gracious</hi> and <hi>Holy Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations,</hi> they are properly Regiſtred for our <hi>imitation;</hi> to the intent we ſhould <hi>tread in their ſteps,</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. For this cauſe have I ſent unto you <hi>Timotheus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>who ſhall bring you into remembrance of my waies which be in Chriſt</hi>) and might be taught by <hi>Pattern,</hi> as well as by <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Abraham</hi> ſtands in Scripture as a pattern for our <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>ſelf-denyal. David</hi> for a pattern of our <hi>ſincerity, a man after Gods own heart.</hi> Encch <hi>of our walking with God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>VVhy now, if we mind them not, and care not to imitate them, we ſin againſt the deſign of the Scripture, and bid God (as it were) keep his Copies to himſelf, we need them not; or we deſire not to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llow them.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:105540:10"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105540:10"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:105540:11"/>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">3. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Patterns make any worke more eaſie.</note>3. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> To be followers of the Saints is a marvelous <hi>help and furtherance in our work.</hi> His work is half done that hath a <hi>preſident</hi> before him; the precept poſſibly may be dark and obſcure; but precept <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplified into a pattern and example,</hi> is plain and facile; he that runs may read.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Patterns are the commands of God made legible</hi> in the lives of the Saints: <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs made exemplary,</hi> by which we may ſee how the Saints <hi>believed,</hi> how the Saints <hi>denyed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hemſelves,</hi> how they <hi>loved God,</hi> and how they contemned <hi>the world, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you would know what ſuch graces are, look upon the Saints, and they will ſerve as ſo many Coments, and Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to you. Beſides, Preſidents do <hi>put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> kind of life into men;</hi> the very bruit crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are animated and quickned by their fellow-creatures, their companions in labours and travel.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">4. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake.</note>4. <hi>Reaſon,</hi> It is a notable means to prevent miſtakes of our own eſtates, and to undeceive us <hi>of falſe opinions of our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are very prone to think well of our ſelves, till we bring our ſelves and our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105540:11"/>wayes to the <hi>pattern</hi> and <hi>exemplar</hi> of the Saints and ſervants of God; then we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſay to our ſelves, Are we like the Saints in <hi>Scripture?</hi> or the Saints <hi>living?</hi> Do I live as they lived? Do I deny my ſelf as they did? Doth my zeal for God eat me up? Is my faith and patience like theirs, that have inherited the Promiſes? Have I a <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpirit? Oh how unlike! what Dwarfs and Pigmies are we in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of them! Surely, either theſe were <hi>more</hi> then Saints, or we are <hi>none:</hi> by comparing, we come to ſee a wide and manifeſt difference between them and us.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">5 <hi>Ground.</hi> God is ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively glorified in the world.</note>5. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> By imitating the Saints, <hi>God is ſucceſſively glorified in the world. Abraham</hi> glorified God in his Generation, and they that walk in the ſteps of faithful <hi>Abraham,</hi> they glorifie him ſucceſſively in their Generations. Though <hi>Abraham</hi> be gone, and the Saints be not; Imitation makes them live ſtill; <hi>Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the multiplication of the Saints:</hi> As the Kings Picture is multiplied by taking <hi>Copies,</hi> ſo that when the King is dead his Effigies will be known in future Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is the Generation of them that ſeek
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105540:12"/>thy face,</hi> O Jacob. The <hi>followers</hi> of <hi>Jacob,</hi> are his <hi>Geceration:</hi> he begot them by his <hi>example</hi> and <hi>Imitation</hi> makes them his <hi>Genuine</hi> Poſterity: They ſtand up as <hi>wreſtlers with God,</hi> as he was. And thus <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lievers,</hi> the Children of <hi>Abraham</hi> his ſpiritual ſeed, his lively Pictures and Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies in the world. <hi>Et ſic in caet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">6 <hi>Ground.</hi> Imitation is the way to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſlothful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note>6. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Imitation is the way to cure us of <hi>ſluggiſhneſs</hi> and <hi>torpor</hi> which is in out natures; <hi>that ye be n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſlothful, but followers</hi> of them, &amp;c. ſo in the text.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſlothfulneſs</hi> here diſſwaded, is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to the forementioned <hi>dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence:</hi> And mention is therefore made of it to ſhew us that for the more proſperous flouriſhing of any Grace, the contrary ſin is very carefully to be ſhunned.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie of <hi>Miltiades</hi> awa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>sto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les. Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>arch.</hi>
               </note>If we would be diligent, we muſt take <hi>heed of ſloth;</hi> and if we would take heed of the ſluggiſhneſs, to which our corrupt natures are ſo marvellouſly propenſe, we muſt eye the <hi>Saints,</hi> imitate them, follow them, and be ſlothfull if you can.</p>
            <p>Conſider what pains the Saints have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in their ſeveral Generations. <hi>Jacob wreſtled</hi> with the Angel till break of day; Chriſt <hi>prayed till he ſweat again.</hi> All
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105540:12"/>he Saints in the Old and New-Teſtament, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey did much,</hi> and <hi>endured much:</hi> take the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reat Apoſtle, it would even tire one of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to read the Catalogue of his active and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſſive travells in the Goſpel, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3. to the end. Oh what have the Saints <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one and ſuffered in their ſeveral ages! How may ſuch Preſidents both ſhame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd quicken us! Oh their labour of love, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir work of faith, their patience of hope! How ſteadfaſt! How unmoveable! How aboundant in the work of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord!</p>
            <p>The keeping of ſuch patterns ſtill in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur eyes will marvellouſly quicken us, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe all diligence in our <hi>Chriſtian race<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Did they run after the rate that we do? Did they pray after the ſame rate that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve pray? Did they pleaſe <hi>themſelves?</hi> O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny ſluggiſh heart! this pace will never <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring thee to heaven.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">7. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Imitation will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy.</note>7. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> The cloſe following of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aints will prevent <hi>Apoſtacy: Joaſh</hi> did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell all the dayes of <hi>Jehoiad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſtians look about you, ye are in great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anger of falling away from your own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tedfaſtneſs. Your temptations are many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd great, and the danger is dreadfull.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:105540:13"/>
            <p>Here in the <hi>Text,</hi> the <hi>ſin,</hi> the <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> who can expound them to us?</p>
            <p>Well, if you will ſtand faſt, eye your <hi>Preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See what they did and ſuffered in their hour of temptation, rather then turn back upon the profeſſion of Religion. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what the Patriarchs, Prophets, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Martyrs of Chriſt have ſuffered, and <hi>ſtand faſt.</hi> Remember how they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved! How they died! As the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted concerning Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Conſider them, what they endured, leſt ye faint in your mindes.</hi> Their <hi>perſeveranc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> well ſaid to heart, will be your <hi>Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">8. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> By this means the loſs of the Saints will be leſs felt.</note>8. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Our following the Saints by holy imitation, <hi>will wake them be leſs miſſed in the world,</hi> when they are taken away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elijah</hi> was leſs wanted becauſe <hi>Eliſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> vvas endued with his ſpirit. <hi>Moſes</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence vvas recruited by <hi>Joſhuas</hi> ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>O do you ſtand in the gap, and fill up the breach of them that are gone, with your gracious influences; and their abſence will be the better born.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:105540:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>My ſeed ſhall ſerve him,</hi> ſaid Chriſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Croſs, or going to it. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 22.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>q. d.</hi> Though I am going out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orld, I ſhall leave a ſpiritual Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> behind me, that will carry on my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ers work in the world. It was Chriſt his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mfort upon the Croſs.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">9. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> By imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of others we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary.</note>9. <hi>Reaſon.</hi> By imitating of the Saints, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e out ſelve; ſhall have the honour of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g exemplary unto others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See how the one is inſeperably annext <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>to the other in that famous <hi>enc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mium</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich the Apoſtle gives his <hi>Theſſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nians, Theſ.</hi> 16 <hi>Ye became follo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rs of us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d of the Lord,</hi> verſe 6. there he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ends their <hi>piety;</hi> And what follows? Why verſe 7. <hi>So that ye became enſamples all that believe in Mac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>donia, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere he celebrateth their <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is our <hi>grace</hi> to <hi>imita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> others, it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r <hi>glory</hi> to be <hi>patterns</hi> to <hi>others.</hi> This is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Crown, the Apoſtle ſets upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ads of his excellent <hi>Theſſalorians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it ſhall be <hi>your Crown</hi> alſo, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith an holy ambition ye contend to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>llowers of them who excell in vertue; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r thereby you alſo will become <hi>ſtanding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atterns and preſidents for others imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105540:14"/>The <hi>Baptiſt</hi> followed the Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>excelled</hi> them; of common <hi>Soldier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> you will become <hi>Captains</hi> and <hi>Leaders</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Lords Army. By intenſive and vig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous imitation, you will transform you ſelves into ſhining and glorious <hi>Lumin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> by whoſe light others may ſee the way to Heaven.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">10. <hi>Reaſ.</hi> Imitation is the way to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</note>10. <hi>Reaſon, This is the way to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Kingdom.</hi> This way all the Saints and wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies of God went, and are now entre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into glory: the foot-ſteps of Companion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is ſuggeſted by Chriſt as an infallible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct in her way. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.8. Go you in the Path, tread in their ſteps and you ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alſo. This is the encouragement whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the text holds out.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be ye followers of them who throug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faith and patience inherit the Promiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (q. d.) <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob</hi> and othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Primitive <hi>Heroes,</hi> have by their hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diligence and inconquerable induſtry in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wayes of holineſs, attained <hi>aſſurance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Heaven</hi> while they lived, and poſſeſſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Heaven</hi> when they died: They have fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed their courſe, and received their <hi>robe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and their <hi>Crowns;</hi> By faith and patience in well-doing, they <hi>inherit the promiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:105540:14"/>
            <p>Preſs hard after them, follow them cloſe, and you ſhall be partakers of the <hi>inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the Saints in light:</hi> You ſhall alſo in the end of your <hi>dayes, receive the end of your hope, even the Salvation of your Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus our Lord encourageth his Soldiers, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 21. <hi>To him that overcometh, will I grant to ſit with me in my Throne, as I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercame,</hi> and am <hi>ſet down with my Father in his Throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Follow me in my <hi>Conflict</hi> and <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> and you ſhall ſhare with me in my <hi>Reward</hi> and <hi>Triumph. If we be dead with Christ, we ſhall aſlo live with Chriſt; if we ſuffer with him we ſhall alſo reign with him;</hi> 2 Tim. 2.11, 12.</p>
            <p>This may ſuffice for the firſt <hi>Querie</hi> Why? the Reaſons and Grounds of the point.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. <hi>Quest.</hi> Wherein the Saints are to be imitated?</note>I come now to the ſecond <hi>Querie,</hi> Wherein? or in what things we are to imitate the Saints?</p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer,
<list>
                  <item>1 Negatively.</item>
                  <item>2 Affirmatively.<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                        <hi>Anſw. Negat.</hi> wherein Not.</note>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Negatively, The Saints are not to be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105540:15"/>imitated in <hi>every thing.</hi> Ex. Gra.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">1. Not in their ſins.</note>1. The Saints are not to be imitated in <hi>their ſins</hi> and <hi>infirmities.</hi> The beſt of Gods ſervants have had their failings and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and they are held out in Scripture to our obſervation; As</p>
            <p>Abraham's <hi>diffidence,</hi> Gen. 12.11, 12, 13. ch. 20.2. Job's <hi>impatience,</hi> Iob. 3.1, 2. Noah's <hi>tranſgreſſing by Wine,</hi> Gen. 9.21. Lot's <hi>inceſt, Gen.</hi> 19.33.35. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid's <hi>Murder and Adultery,</hi> 2 Sam. 11.15, 4. Elijahs <hi>Paſſion.</hi> Jam. 5.17. Peter's <hi>denying his Lord,</hi> Mat. 27.70, 72, 74.</p>
            <p>Theſe and many other failings and falls of the Saints, are Recorded in the Book of God: But they are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the ſupport and comfort of lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Chriſtians, that reflecting upon their own ſurpriſes by temptation, they may not <hi>deſpond</hi> and <hi>deſpair,</hi> as if their <hi>ſpot were not the ſpot of Gods Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. For the <hi>caution and admonition</hi> of all ſurviving generations; to the intent that <hi>we ſhould</hi> not preſume to <hi>ſin as they ſinned.</hi> 1 Cor. 10.6.</p>
            <p>But to be ſure they ſtand not in the holy Regiſter, as <hi>Patterns</hi> and <hi>encouragements</hi> to ſin. They are our <hi>Take-heeds,</hi> not our <hi>Warrants;</hi> they tell us, here is a <hi>Rock,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105540:15"/>it; here is a <hi>Quick-ſand, come not near it,</hi> leſt you ſuffer <hi>ſhipwrack. We</hi> are not to imitate the <hi>beſt</hi> in their <hi>worſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. Not in what they did by miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration.</note>2. They are not be imitated in what they did by immediate and miraculous aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>As we are commanded to <hi>be followers of God</hi> as <hi>dear Children,</hi> but not in the <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the world;</hi> not in <hi>cauſing the Sun to riſe,</hi> and the <hi>Rain to fall,</hi> &amp;c. that is, we muſt not attempt ſuch an imitation of our heavenly Father, as being above the Sphere of the creature, the <hi>Prerogative</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the great God.</p>
            <p>Our Lord commandeth us to <hi>learn of him,</hi> but not in <hi>raiſing the dead;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11.29.</note> not in <hi>multiplying loaves,</hi> not in <hi>caſting out De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils by a word,</hi> &amp;c. theſe being works which Chriſt did not in his <hi>Private,</hi> but in his <hi>Mediatory Capacity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So alſo the <hi>Prophets, Apoſtles</hi> and other of the Saints of God, though they be out <hi>Standards</hi> and Patterns, yet they are not to be followed in thoſe actions which they did by vertue of an extraordinary <hi>afflatus</hi> or <hi>inſpiration</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt; thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions being peculiar only to their extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary <hi>commiſſions</hi> and <hi>functions,</hi> and not common to them as <hi>believers.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:105540:16"/>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Not in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pecial di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>penſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>3. Neither are they to be followed in thoſe actions which they did by ſpecial <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation,</hi> or by way of <hi>probation</hi> and <hi>tryal.</hi> Ex. Gra. VVe are not to rob, ſpoil and take away the ſubſtance and eſtates of <hi>wicked men,</hi> (meerly <hi>quà wicked</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Iſraelites robbed the Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> unleſs we had <hi>immediate Authority and command</hi> for it, from him, who is the abſolute and <hi>Supream Lord</hi> of the Creature,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 75.7</note> and may diſpoſe of the whole Creation to whomſoever he pleaſe, <hi>as they had.</hi> We may not offer up our <hi>Sons and Daughters in ſacrifice to God,</hi> becauſe <hi>God tempted Abraham</hi> to offer up his <hi>Iſaac,</hi> for <hi>tryal</hi> of his <hi>obedience</hi> and <hi>Self-denyal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor yet again may any man or woman <hi>take a Wife or Husband of Whoredome,</hi> as the Prophet did, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.2. (whether in <hi>viſion</hi> only, or in <hi>reality</hi> we enquire not here) uneſs we had the ſame <hi>ſpecial diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation</hi> and allowance from the Supream <hi>Law-giver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Negatively,</hi> We are not <hi>to follow</hi> the Saints.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Affirmatively,</hi> Therefore, we are to imitate the Saints <hi>in their graces</hi> only, and in their <hi>holy Converſations</hi> in the world, and in whatever they did in a way of <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:105540:16"/>and <hi>conformity</hi> to the <hi>revealed will of God,</hi> the ſtanding rule of the <hi>word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A more diſtinct and particular account whereof, I ſhall give, before I finiſh this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin" type="runSum">3 Qu. How we muſt imitate the Saints</note> Querie. <hi>How muſt we imitate the Saints of God?</hi> Anſwer. Here again our <hi>Negative Rule</hi> meets us, <hi>(ſcil.)</hi> We are not to follow the Saints <hi>Univerſally; not all over.</hi> And the reaſon is, becauſe, <hi>all that is in the Saints,</hi> is not <hi>Sanctity.</hi> All that is in the <hi>Godly,</hi> is not <hi>Godlineſs.</hi> Saints have their <hi>infirmities,</hi> and in <hi>them</hi> they are not to be imitated.</p>
            <p>The <hi>beſt of men, are but men at the beſt. Affirmatively,</hi> Therefore our imitation of the Saints it muſt be but,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">With li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation.</note>1. A <hi>limited Imitation.</hi> And that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation, one of the beſt of men (that were but men) the great Apoſtle hath given us in his own Perſon:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1</note> 
               <hi>Be ye followers of me,</hi> (How?) <hi>as I am of Chriſt.</hi> If we find holy <hi>Paul,</hi> not following <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he doth not require us to follow <hi>him.</hi> It was <hi>Jehoſophat's</hi> honour that he made choice of the firſt wayes of <hi>David</hi> to walk in. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we have theſe intermediate Copies written for our <hi>learning:</hi> God therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105540:17"/>to our infirmity, leſt our tender eies ſhould be too much dazled in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al beholding the tranſcendent brightneſſe of the <hi>Supream light,</hi> 1 Joh. 1.5. But <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit</hi> are the Supream <hi>Original Standard</hi> of our Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Father.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.48</note> 
               <hi>Be you perfect as your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is in heaven is perfect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15</note> As he <hi>which hath called you, is holy, ſo be ye holy in all manner of</hi> Converſation.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7.14</note> They that are <hi>after the Spirit, do mind the things of the Spirit.</hi> And again, As many as are <hi>led by the Spirit</hi> are the Sons of God.</p>
            <p>Next to theſe, the Saints and Angels in Heaven, are our lights of a ſecond magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Petit..</hi> 3d.</note> 
               <hi>Thy will be done on Earth, as it is done in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are our exact and perfect Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plars, in which there is no <hi>defect or imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But all our <hi>Earthly Patterns</hi> (be they never ſo excellent) have their <hi>errours</hi> and <hi>deficiencies;</hi> which may miſlead us, if we follow them without due limitation. And therefore all theſe <hi>inferi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur Patterns,</hi> are to be <hi>reduced to the Original Standard and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105540:17"/>Exemplar;</hi> and wherein they are found either <hi>erroneous</hi> or <hi>defective,</hi> we are to correct and perfect them by the <hi>Original;</hi> we muſt by faith eye the <hi>Pattern</hi> in the <hi>Mount:</hi> we may imitate our <hi>terreſtrial Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies,</hi> but we muſt not <hi>terminate</hi> in them. The Saints are <hi>good</hi> Leaders, but not <hi>infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible</hi> uſeful <hi>Copies,</hi> but ſuch as have need to be corrected by the <hi>Original.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our imitation of them therefore, muſt be <hi>bounded</hi> by <hi>Scripture-limitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form.</hi> Nemo agit unum niſi ſapiens, caeterimul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiformes ſunt, Sen. Ep. Phil. <hi>4.8.</hi>
               </note>2. Our Imitation of the Saints muſt be <hi>exact and uniform:</hi> though we are not to imitate the Saints in <hi>all their actions,</hi> yet we are to imitate them in all their <hi>Graces, and gracious converſation. Whatſoever things are true, whatſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ever things are juſt. Whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report, if there be any virtue, if there be any praiſe</hi> in the Saints and Servants of God, theſe things we muſt think of; and in theſe things we muſt labour <hi>to be like unto them.</hi> We muſt take heed of <hi>Partiality,</hi> in our following the Saints; of <hi>preferring one before another,</hi> one <hi>Saint</hi> before ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; or one <hi>Grace</hi> in the Saints before another, unleſs it be <hi>ſuch</hi> Saints, and <hi>ſuch</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:105540:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:105540:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:105540:19"/>Graces, as <hi>God himſelf</hi> hath <hi>preferred</hi> by putting upon them more abundant honour, ſome ſpecial remark of excellency; we muſt take heed of <hi>picking</hi> and <hi>chuſing,</hi> taking what vve <hi>pleaſe,</hi> and rejecting what we <hi>liſt,</hi> according to our own private fancies and intereſt: We muſt follow them in <hi>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry path,</hi> and in every <hi>ſtep,</hi> wherein they have f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llowed the Captain of their ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Whether in their <hi>doing-work,</hi> or in their <hi>ſuffering-work</hi> St. <hi>Paul's</hi> charge to <hi>Timothy</hi> will not in this caſe be improper for us; I <hi>charge thee before God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21</note> 
               <hi>and the elect Angels, that thou obſerve theſe things without preferring one before another, doing nothing by Pa tia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</hi> To this end,</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. Vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</note>3. Our <hi>Imitation</hi> of the Saints muſt be a <hi>vigorous and induſtrious Imitation.</hi> Truly to follow the Saints <hi>fully</hi> and <hi>exactly,</hi> is not a buſineſs of an eaſie and ordinary diſpatch, it will require a vigorous and induſtrious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and contention of our ſpirits, as a work that will take up all the faculties of our ſouls, and parts of our bodies: Our <hi>Judgments</hi> to diſcern (according to the word) what is to be <hi>choſen,</hi> and what to be <hi>eſchewed</hi> in the Patterns we propound to our ſelves: Our <hi>Unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtandings,</hi> to <hi>diſcover
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105540:19"/>the beauty and amiableneſs</hi> of the Graces and Holineſs that is in the Saints. Our <hi>Memories,</hi> to keep alwaies before our eyes theſe excellent Preſidents, <hi>leſt at any time we let them ſlip;</hi> we ſhall ſtand in need of ſuch Looking-glaſſes continually, to ſee our faces in; we ſhall want our Guides at every turning, to tell us the way, when we are turning to the <hi>right hand,</hi> or to the <hi>left.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Wills and Affection,</hi> to love our Guides, to take delight and compl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cency in beholding theſe beautifull pieces; if we ſee no <hi>beauty</hi> in the <hi>Saints,</hi> why we ſhould deſire them, we ſhall never be zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous imitators of their Perſons.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Conſciences:</hi> we ſtand in need of the impartial Teſtimony of an awakened conſcience, to <hi>accuſe</hi> or <hi>excuſe</hi> us according to our <hi>fidelity</hi> or <hi>neglect</hi> in this duty of ſo great concernment. Moreover it will coſt us much <hi>prayer, medita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion,</hi> often <hi>reflection</hi> upon our <hi>ſelves, watchfull obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, ſelf-denial, mortification, &amp;c.</hi> Yea, much <hi>labour</hi> and <hi>pains</hi> even of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man <hi>much faſting, ſtriving, wreſtling, and watchfulneſs,</hi> to carry on this great important duty, of imitating the Saints. Surely a ſlothful, lazy profeſſor, will never
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105540:20"/>make any earnings in ſo curious and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious a work as this is.</p>
            <p>That's h ghly obſervable in the Text; That ye be not <hi>ſlothful, but followers</hi> of them who through f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith and patience, &amp;c. <hi>Sloth,</hi> and <hi>Imitation</hi> of the Saint are incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent.</p>
            <p>It is a mattet of great labour and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to be a follower of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and all the reſt of the <hi>Heroes</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>od Worthies of God, in their faith, and patience, and other Graces: A deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate ſhort ſpirited profeſſour will never carry on this ſpiritual and bleſſed trade to any purpoſe; therefore ſayes the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle (he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e) We deſire that every one of you do ſhew the ſame <hi>diligence,</hi> &amp;c. All the ſtrength and induſtry you have, will be little enough to lay out in this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duous and excellent deſign.</p>
            <p>Aſſure your ſelves, it will afford you no time for <hi>ſecurity,</hi> and the <hi>indulging</hi> of the <hi>fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It coſt the Saints much holy contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to write and leave theſe excellent <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies</hi> to the ſucceeding world; and it will coſt you no leſs induſtry to write <hi>exactly after them.</hi> You muſt not think to make to your ſelves a <hi>religion</hi> of your <hi>own,</hi> or
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105540:20"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> take up this imitation, and lay it down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gain when you pleaſe. Therefore,</p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">4. Our I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation muſt be conſtant.</note>4. Our Imitation of the Saints muſt be <hi>conſtant and perſevering</hi> Imitation; ſo in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he verſe before my text.</p>
            <p>We deſire every one of you, uſe the ſame <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ligence to the end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where ever you ceaſe this Imitation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou diſclaim your Patterns; and expoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our ſelves to the ſin and danger of <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Our Imitation of the Saints muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e a <hi>believing</hi>-Imitation.<note place="margin">5. Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> As we muſt i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate their <hi>Faith,</hi> ſo we muſt have faith <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o imitate them.</hi> Faith to <hi>realize the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe,</hi> and faith to <hi>believe Gods Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſs</hi> and <hi>All-ſufficiency</hi> to make good his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>romiſe; ſo did <hi>Abraham, Rom.</hi> 4.20.</p>
            <p>Our Imitation of the Saints will meet with <hi>much oppoſition,</hi> many <hi>diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> from our <hi>fleſh, contradiction</hi> from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>world,</hi> and <hi>oppoſition</hi> from the <hi>Devil:</hi> We muſt have faith to overcome them all, or elſe we ſhall eaſily give out, and ſit down with <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>loſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly and laſtly,<note place="margin">6. Patient</note> Our Imitation of the Saints, muſt be <hi>a patient Imitation.</hi> As we muſt Imitate the Saints in their <hi>Patience,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:105540:21"/>ſo there is great <hi>need of Patience</hi> to <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in this Imitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Saints have in their ſeveral Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations met with much trouble, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution in following <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo ſhall you in following them.</p>
            <p>You have need therefore of Patience, that when ye have done the vvill of God you may receive the Promiſe. <hi>Here is the Faith and Patience of the Saints,</hi> through which they inherit the Promiſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Patience to <hi>ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> and faith to <hi>conquer</hi> their ſufferrings: Faith to <hi>believe the recompence of Reward,</hi> and Patience to <hi>wait till it come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Go ye, and do likewiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much for the Doctrine; I come now to the Uſe.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:105540:21"/>
            <p>Come now to the <hi>Uſe</hi> of the Point. <note place="margin" type="runSum">Uſe 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And in the firſt place it may ſerve way of <hi>Information,</hi> to ſhew us, That</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All commendation of departed Saints not to be condemned.</hi> For ſurely is not meerly <hi>upon their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ount,</hi> that their Perſons are celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed with ſuch remarks of honour, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir <hi>names perpetu ted to poſterity</hi> by a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ratefull Commemoration. If it were, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey are not to be envied their juſt <hi>Enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iums:</hi> Since God is pleaſed to ſet the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rown of Glory</hi> upon their Graces in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en,</hi> we have no cauſe to think it too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reat an honour to ſet the <hi>Crown of Praiſe</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon their Graces here on <hi>Earth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. ul ult.</note> Yea, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e have the Divine allowance for it. <hi>Let their workes praiſe them in the Gates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is upon an higher account that honourable mention,<note place="margin">Two grounds upon which commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Saints is warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</note> and Commemorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is to be made of the Graces, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies of the Saints.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In as much as ſuch <hi>Encomiums are rather the Commenda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105540:22"/>Grace of God</hi> in the Saints, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Saints themſelves. And by this mean <hi>Chriſt is glorified in his Saints, and adm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all them which believe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10</note> And ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not unto the Saints, not to the Saint but to the God of the Saints is all the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be aſcribed.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. Becauſe by this means o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are provoked to holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note>2. Becauſe this Commendation of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Saints is for the <hi>propagation of their pie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and holineſs to</hi> them that <hi>do ſurvive, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſhall be born in after-generaions, that the <hi>may inherit the benefit of ſuch excelle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Patterns, to provoke them to an holy Im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore to bury the Saints <hi>grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in the ſame <hi>grave of Oblivion</hi> with their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, is to obſcure the Starrs, and to <hi>rob</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> world of the light and influence of ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> glorious <hi>Luminaries,</hi> which God hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſet up in the firmament of the Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Yea, to <hi>Eclipſe the Sun of Righteouſneſſ Himſelf,</hi> by whoſe <hi>aſpect</hi> they ſhone ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bright to the world.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Things have made commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</note>There be two wayes indeed, whereb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the uſe of the Commendation of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Saints departed, hath become perniciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the world.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whileſt ſome <hi>greedy Preachers</hi> (fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> filthy lucre-ſake) have turned even <hi>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:105540:22"/>vices</hi> into <hi>vertues;</hi> boldly making <hi>Saints</hi> where God hath <hi>made none.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. When vice paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth for vertue.</note> Whileſt not only every <hi>Briſtol-ſtone</hi> muſt paſs for a <hi>Diamond,</hi> and every <hi>Glow-worm</hi> be mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified to a <hi>Star;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But even Drunkards, Adulterers, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wearers, and the Covetous, (whom the Lord abhorreth) <hi>their bodies muſt not be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut into the grave, before th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir ſouls have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en ſeated upon Thrones in glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How many thouſands, this kind of <hi>Pulpit-flattery</hi> hath ruined, may (not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitably) be preſumed. Since by this means the worſt of men fear not to live in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he groſſeſt ſins whileſt they can purchaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Prieſts Abſolution at ſo cheap a rate when they come to <hi>die,</hi> and their ſouls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſent to Heaven <hi>by Letters of commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> from a <hi>Mercenary Clergie-man</hi> when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey are <hi>dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. While commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, hath ſtol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into adoration</note>2. Another way whereby Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of the dead hath proved ſo fatal to poor deceived ſouls, is,</p>
            <p>Whileſt <hi>Commending of the Saints</hi> hath ſupeſtitiouſly <hi>Commenced into ſacrilegious worſhiping of them, and Praying to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Apotheoſis</hi> in <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me Ethnic<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and <hi>Canonization</hi> of Saints in <hi>Rome Catholique,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:105540:23"/>hath ſprung principally from this Fountain;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eque ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ande est <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> plera<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceii, fun. orat. Maceo. v.</note> whileſt in both, the fond oppinion, and overlaviſh Commendation, which the preſent generation gave to their <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies</hi> and <hi>Be efactors,</hi> have enſnared the Ignorance of ſucceeeding generations, to judge them not unworthy of <hi>Divine honou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>ador<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion;</hi> while they thought that their tranſlation into thoſe Coeleſtial habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, could not but improve their <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignity</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> for the help of poor <hi>mortals</hi> here below, even to <hi>Infinitude,</hi> who were of ſuch Heroick Influence, whileſt yet amongſt the Sons of men. Hence the Original of worſhiping the dead, and praying to them. Save only, that the <hi>Pride,</hi> and <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ice</hi> of the latter <hi>Pontificians,</hi> hath prevailed with them to Canonize for <hi>Saints,</hi> ſuch as they knew to be the <hi>worſt of men;</hi> and to create them little <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ities,</hi> who by the juſteſt Character which could be collected out of their <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> and <hi>lives,</hi> are now amongſt <hi>Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate Spirits, ſuffering the vengeance of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely, <hi>thus to commend the dead,</hi> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs <hi>then</hi> to <hi>blaſpheme God,</hi> and to enrich the Devils Territories <hi>with Caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:105540:23"/>
            <p>The true end of celebrating the Graces of the Saints is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God may have the <hi>Glory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</note> whileſt the Saints <hi>ſhew forth the praiſes, or vertues of him who hath called them out of darkneſs into his marvelous light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That the world may have the <hi>benefit and advantage</hi> of their worthy Patterns and Exemplars; <hi>ut ſup.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thanks be to God for ſuch excellent helps in our way to heaven.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Uſe.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Uſe Repr.</note> It may ſerve to Reprove divers ſorts of people.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">1 Such as account the Saints the worſt of men.</note>1. Such as account the <hi>Saints of God the moſt dangerous kind of men in the world;</hi> not fit for <hi>humane ſociety.</hi> Surely there is not ſuch a <hi>reviled, perſecuted, defamed</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration again under heaven; The very <hi>filth</hi> and <hi>off-ſcouring</hi> of all things,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.12 13.</note> the <hi>dregs,</hi> the <hi>ſordes,</hi> the <hi>ſcraping</hi> of the ſhoes;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the <hi>ſuperfluous froth</hi> and <hi>ſcum,</hi> that is good for nothing but to be caſt into the fire: Yea the more <hi>holy,</hi> the <hi>worſe.</hi> The Saints are look't upon as the <hi>Troublers</hi> of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> the Peſts of the places where they live, the Deformities of humane ſociety.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 1, 16.</note> Surely, theſe men are not of Gods mind, God accounts them as his Jewels,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.14</note> the Starrs in his right hand, the <hi>Sons of God,</hi> the <hi>lights
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105540:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:105540:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:105540:25"/>the world,</hi> to give light to a dark world: <hi>Patterns</hi> and <hi>Exemplars,</hi> worthy to be held forth to the <hi>obſervation</hi> and <hi>imitation,</hi> of the Sons of men; (as here)</p>
            <p>In a word men think the Saints not <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 22.22 <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.38 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 44.</note> when in the mean time, Gods thinks the <hi>world</hi> not <hi>worthy of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh how hath the God of the world blinded the eyes of them that believe not!</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2 Such as imitate the worſt.</note>2. It may ſerve to reprove ſuch as do not care <hi>whom they follow,</hi> or what Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns in the world they do imitate; none ſo <hi>vile,</hi> ſo <hi>debaucht,</hi> ſo <hi>prophane,</hi> ſo great a derider and perſecutor of holineſs, but is good enough to make a <hi>Copy</hi> for them to write after; men do as they ſee the major part of men do, <hi>they follow the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> as thinking it not good to be <hi>ſingular,</hi> and <hi>ſtricter</hi> then their neighbours; though that be a rule upon which God hath ſet a ſpecial brand of infamy. <hi>Fellow not a multitude to do evil.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Eſpecially the <hi>great</hi> and <hi>learned</hi> men of the world; men are prone to look upon <hi>them</hi> as infallible Guides, and do greedily follow their conduct. <hi>Have any of the Rulers believed on him?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.48.</note> Great men have followers of their <hi>vices,</hi> as well as of their <hi>Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:105540:25"/>
            <p>Alas, we ſhould take our Patterns from Heaven; <hi>Thy will be done on Earth as it is in Heaven;</hi> and the greateſt of men do not care out of what filthy <hi>ditch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Spiritus ſunt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinceri vagi a coelesti vigori &amp; virtute de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituti &amp;c. ad Sola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatis ſuae nil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſinum perditi prodere, <hi>Min. Fel. 3. Them that imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the beſt, but in the worſt.</hi>
               </note> or from what <hi>dunghill,</hi> they take up their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; even from <hi>Hell</hi> it ſelf people are not afraid to fetch their Patterns; as proud as the <hi>Devil,</hi> as malicious as the <hi>Devil,</hi> as <hi>blaſphemous</hi> as the damned Reprobates themſelves, as hating of God and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as the Angels that kept not their firſt eſtate, as greedy and induſtrious to drag o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with them into perdition! This is a lamentation and ſhall be for a lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It may reprove ſuch, as (it may be) will imitate the Saints, but not in their <hi>Sanctity,</hi> but in their <hi>ſins: Lot</hi> in his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt, Noah</hi> in his <hi>Drunkenneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> in his <hi>Adultery,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> in his <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying his Maſter,</hi> &amp;c. And when they have done, can <hi>quote</hi> ſuch <hi>instances</hi> for their <hi>Authority!</hi> Oh the wonderful per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſs that is in our Apoſtate natures, that men ſhould imitate the Saints only in their <hi>deformities!</hi> Imitate Saints only, in that wherein they are not Saints! Is there any ſuch thing in nature!</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:105540:26"/>
            <p>Are there any amongſt men that deſire to be like others in their natural defects and deformities, be they perſons never ſo great? Do you obſerve any that take de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to imitate men under <hi>diſtraction,</hi> or <hi>mad men?</hi> Did it ever eaſe any that lay ſick of the <hi>Gout, Stone, Strangurie, Dropſie, Fever, &amp;c.</hi> to tell them that many <hi>Noble, Rich, learned Perſons</hi> have been tormented with the like pains?</p>
            <p>Surely,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Object.</note> you will ſay, no wonder if not, ſince theſe are the <hi>blemiſhes, infelicities</hi> and <hi>deſtruction</hi> of the humane nature.</p>
            <p>And are not <hi>mens luſts</hi> and <hi>corruptions ſo too?</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſwer.</note> Even of the Saints themſelves, ſave only by interpoſition of <hi>divine grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.3.</note> healing and reſtoring them! Yea, and of ſo much worſe <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>effect,</hi> then ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>intellectual</hi> or <hi>bodily</hi> diſtempers, by how much the <hi>ſoul</hi> is <hi>better</hi> then the <hi>body,</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> worſe then <hi>Death;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18</note> 
               <hi>God himſelf</hi> teſtifying it from <hi>Heaven:</hi> And the Saints themſelves, <hi>after they have recovered their lapſes,</hi> having confeſt it before all the world, with greateſt ſelf-abhorrency and abaſement.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 73.22.</note> 
               <hi>So fooliſh was I, and ignorant, and like a beaſt before thee,</hi> cries <hi>David</hi> when he came out of the <hi>Sanctuary;</hi> he is ſo incenſt againſt his ſin that he cannot
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105540:26"/>find a term vile enough to reproach himſelf withall!</p>
            <p>And yet is <hi>ſin</hi> the <hi>only imitable thing</hi> men can diſcover in the Saints?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.22</note> How long ye ſimple ones will <hi>ye love ſimplicity, and Scorners delight in ſcorning, and fools hate knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lord, who hath believed <hi>thy</hi> report? or to whom is the Arm of the Lord reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Reproof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. That will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the beſt but in the beſt.</note>But there is yet another ſort of people, that juſtly merit the <hi>laſh of reproof;</hi> and they are ſuch who though they dare not be ſo <hi>bad</hi> as to imitate the Saints in their <hi>ſins,</hi> yet love not to be ſo <hi>good,</hi> as to imitate the Saints in their <hi>ſtrictneſs,</hi> and holy <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity</hi> in Religion. They think it enough to follow them in their <hi>morality,</hi> and <hi>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil deportment,</hi> to be juſt and true in their dealings, to be charitable to the poor, and to keep their Church (as they call it;) But their <hi>holineſs,</hi> their <hi>zeal, mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>cloſe walking with God;</hi> to be <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes abounding in the work of the Lord:</hi> Here they leave them, as deeming <hi>theſe,</hi> nothing elſe but the <hi>unneceſſary ſtrains of a fruitleſs preciſeneſſe,</hi> and that which may expoſe them to the <hi>ſcandal</hi> and diſguſt of the world.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:105540:27"/>
            <p>Oh the blindneſs and folly of the <hi>wiſdom of the fleſh!</hi> That wherein the Saints are <hi>moſt like God,</hi> therein, only the unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate world careth leſt to be <hi>like unto them!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which <hi>God</hi> accounteth his <hi>Glory,</hi> (for <hi>that</hi> is his <hi>Name, Glorious in holineſs,</hi> and (therefore) <hi>fearful in praiſes</hi>) the reprobate world account their <hi>abaſement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh ye Sons of men, how long will ye turn <hi>Gods glory</hi> into <hi>ſhame?</hi> how long will ye love vanity and ſeek after leaſing?</p>
            <p>Surely, <hi>carnal men</hi> are <hi>Gods Antipodes,</hi> they <hi>ſtand</hi> upon their <hi>heads,</hi> and <hi>ſhake</hi> their <hi>heeles</hi> againſt <hi>Heaven!</hi> They glory in their <hi>ſhame,</hi> and are <hi>aſhamed</hi> of their glory; they <hi>vilifie</hi> what they ſhould <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire,</hi> and <hi>admire</hi> what they ſhould <hi>vilifie;</hi> they <hi>imitate</hi> whom, and <hi>what</hi> they ſhould <hi>abhor,</hi> and <hi>abhor</hi> what they ſhould <hi>imitate!</hi> Ah how have the Sons of men loſt not their <hi>conſcience</hi> only, but their <hi>judgement!</hi> How have they diveſted themſelves not of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion only, but of Reaſon; and put off the <hi>Man,</hi> as well as the <hi>Saint!</hi> This is a lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and ſhall be for a lamentation! I come now to a more particular Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Doctrine, to our <hi>ſelves</hi> of this <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily,</hi> together with other Relations and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:105540:27"/>Friends, more eſpecially concerned in our ſorrows.</p>
            <p>Suffer I beſeech you, a <hi>word of Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſe Exhor.</note>
            </p>
            <p>My dearly Beloved, God hath made a fore <hi>breach</hi> upon us; He hath <hi>ſmitten us,</hi> and <hi>made us ſick in ſmiting us.</hi> The <hi>Crown</hi> is fallen from our <hi>Head;</hi> The <hi>Ornament of our Family</hi> is taken away: <hi>A Wife, a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th r, a Friend, a Guide,</hi> the <hi>delight of our eyes is gone,</hi> the bleſſing of all her Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at home and Acquaintance abroad! Wo unto us, for we have ſinned!</p>
            <p>And now dear Friends, <hi>what ſhall we do!</hi> Shall we <hi>give up our ſelves to ſorrow?</hi> ſhall we lie down and <hi>roar</hi> as men and woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that have no <hi>hope?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This were to wrong <hi>our ſelves.</hi> Or ſhall we make it our work <hi>to forget Her,</hi> to caſt her out of our thoughts? and to bury her <hi>memory</hi> with her <hi>Aſhes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This were to wrong <hi>Her,</hi> who has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved better at our hands.</p>
            <p>Shall we then ſpend our thoughts and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires where and how we may <hi>recruit our ſelves</hi> with new Relations? and to make up our Lots with other Comforts? or let out our hearts more greedily to them we have yet remaining?</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:105540:28"/>
            <p>This were infinitely to <hi>wrong God,</hi> and to pervert the <hi>deſignes and purpoſes</hi> of his grace in this ſevere diſpenſation. Or ſhall we, laſtly, ſatisfie our ſelves with a <hi>few cold fruitleſs Commendations</hi> of the things which were excellent and praiſe-worthy in Her?</p>
            <p>This were but to mock <hi>our ſelves,</hi> and <hi>Her,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p>Behold, therefore I will yet ſhevv you <hi>a more excellent way,</hi> and it is that in my Text, <hi>Be ye followers of her;</hi> ſtudy to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate ſo excellent a Pattern, as ſhe hath left us, for me thinks I hear her crying to us out of her <hi>grave,</hi> or rather from <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> (where her triumphant ſoul is placed amongſt the ſpirits of juſt men made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect) as ſometimes <hi>Her</hi> Lord, and <hi>ours,</hi> beſpake his Diſciples. <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.15. <hi>I have given you an example that you ſhould do as I have done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now therefore, that I may not beat the aire, nor ſpend time unprofitably (only) in <hi>Generals;</hi> I ſhall propoſe Her to your view, in a twofold Capacity: But with this preface, That here it muſt not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from me, that I ſhould either pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim her <hi>extraction,</hi> which was <hi>generous,</hi> or deſcribe the lovelineſs of her perſon,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:105540:28"/>though I mayſay with modeſty, Her ſoul did <hi>benè habitare,</hi> 'twas lodged in a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful <hi>habitation;</hi> her body which was an elegant piece of natures artifice, did <hi>give</hi> (as well as receive) a <hi>grace</hi> to what ever ſhe <hi>did</hi> or <hi>ſpake.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In her <hi>Relational</hi> Capacity.</item>
               <item>2. In her <hi>Perſonal</hi> Capacity.<note place="margin">Her Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity.</note>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In both which, you will find her wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of your moſt exact and vigorous imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Take her</p>
            <p n="1">1. In her <hi>Relational Capacity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. As a Child.</note> and there look upon her, firſt as a <hi>Child,</hi> and <hi>a moſt du ifull and obedient Child</hi> ſhe was, not only where the Relation was <hi>natural,</hi> but even where it was but <hi>Legal</hi> and <hi>Adoptitious.</hi> She never <hi>diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed</hi> or <hi>neglected</hi> the Commands of her Parents <hi>in the leaſt,</hi> vvhile ſhe was under the charge of their education.</p>
            <p>She was of a moſt <hi>teachable</hi> and <hi>tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> ſpirit; there was nothing of a <hi>perverſe</hi> or <hi>peeviſh diſpoſition</hi> in her; her <hi>Will</hi> vvas bound up in the <hi>Will</hi> of her <hi>Parents,</hi> and <hi>Governours,</hi> ſhe had no will of her own.</p>
            <p>She was a moſt exact obſerver of the fifth Commandment, <hi>in honoring her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother,</hi> in <hi>Word, Geſture</hi> and <hi>Actions,</hi> there was never heard an unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105540:29"/>coming vvord fall from her lips towards them, nor undecent carriage obſerved, nor any thing that might be interpreted as the leaſt defect of that honour which was due unto them by the Law of God and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>But her whole deportment, was fraught with as much <hi>ſweet, reverential, pleaſing</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, as their hearts could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</p>
            <p>You that are <hi>Children,</hi> or under the <hi>juſt obligation</hi> of Children, <hi>ſee</hi> you be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Her in this <hi>Child-like vertue:</hi> Keep this excellent Pattern of <hi>filial obedience</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes before your eyes as a ſingular exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plification of the fifth Commandment, expounded by the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.1.2 3.</note> 
               <hi>Children obey your Parents in the Lord, for this is right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or if this Inſtance of obedience ſeems too inferiour, take that Inſtance of an <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er authority.</hi> That of the <hi>Son of God Incarnate,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, <hi>He went down with</hi> his Parents,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.51.</note> 
               <hi>and came to Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and was ſubject to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. As a Wife.</note>2. Take her in the <hi>Conjugal Relation,</hi> and there you may behold Her a moſt <hi>Chaſt, Loyal, Loving, Tender,</hi> and (according to her <hi>audibly</hi> avowed engagement at her Marriage in the publick Aſſembly) <hi>An
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:105540:29"/>obedient Wife,</hi> as two loving Husbands, have ſucceſſively experienced and teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>She ſtudied <hi>to pleaſe</hi> and <hi>not to be pleaſed;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.19</note> 
               <hi>ſweet as the loving Hinde, and as the pleaſant Ree.</hi> She never <hi>diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nted</hi> from them, but as the <hi>word</hi> did vvarrant her <hi>diſſent;</hi> and then, (if poſſibly ſuch a <hi>then</hi> there vvas,) <hi>propoſing,</hi> rather then <hi>oppoſing; perſwading</hi> by Scripture-rule, rather then <hi>contradicting</hi> by ſelf-vvill.</p>
            <p>Above all, ſhe vvas tenderly <hi>affected</hi> to, and covetuouſly deſirous of the <hi>Spiritual good</hi> of her Conjugal Relations.</p>
            <p>A <hi>true help</hi> ſhe vvas, a <hi>Soul-Help</hi> unto them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.18.</note> anſwering fully to the Law of her Creation; themſelves have ſucceſſively acknowledged, they have had cauſe to bleſs God for her, with the excellent Woman in the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> ch. 31.12. She did them good, and not evill all her daies.</p>
            <p>You that are <hi>Wives,</hi> be ye followers of ſuch a Pattern; ſhe was <hi>ſubject to her own Husband, as the Church is ſubject to Chriſt.</hi> As ſhe did <hi>imitate</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> ſo do ye imitate her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wives be you obedient in all things; to your own Husbands in all things</hi> ſave where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:105540:30"/>in your obedience to them, may poſſibly be <hi>diſobedience</hi> to God; and therein, not oppoſing <hi>your wills,</hi> ſo much to theirs as Gods. That's not <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Superiours,</hi> vvherein not the <hi>will</hi> ſo much of the <hi>Inferiour,</hi> gives ſin a <hi>Negative</hi> vote as the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and Conſcience rightly <hi>informed by the word</hi> of God.</p>
            <p>Yoke-fellows, <hi>Love ye one another ſouls.</hi> Love one another <hi>to heaven,</hi> Let not the fleſh go away with all your <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>ſtrength</hi> and <hi>affections;</hi> nor the <hi>elder ſerve the younger. Live together as heirs of the grace of life, that your prayers be not hindred.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Look upon her as a <hi>Miſtris</hi> in her Family.<note place="margin">3. A Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneſs.</note> She was an excellent <hi>Governeſs,</hi> her government was o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Scripture conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution. It was made up of <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> and <hi>gravity; ſweetneſs</hi> without <hi>levity</hi> or <hi>remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; gravity</hi> without <hi>bitterneſs</hi> and <hi>ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was no <hi>ſeverity</hi> in her diſcipline, ſave what was in the <hi>Pattern</hi> ſhe propoſed to them, her own <hi>Converſation:</hi> Indeed ſhe was <hi>ſeverely good;</hi> her government was made up of <hi>Intreaties,</hi> rather then <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands</hi> or <hi>Repro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> She knew not how to be <hi>angry,</hi> unleſs it were againſt <hi>ſin;</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105540:30"/>
               <hi>that</hi> ſhe expreſt rather in <hi>grief,</hi> then in <hi>paſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Her great Care was, that her family might <hi>know God, and Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.3.</note> 
               <hi>whom to know his life eternal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She was of a <hi>Joſhuah-like</hi> reſolution.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſ.</hi> 24.13</note> 
               <hi>As for me and my houſe, we will ſerve the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She thought it not enough to go to <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven alone,</hi> but laboured to carry as many as ſhe could with her, eſpecially them of <hi>her own Family.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To that end ſhe was very exact and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in <hi>Family-duties,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actneſs in family<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duties.</note> 
               <hi>(ſc.) Reading the Scripture, Prayer, Catechiſing,</hi> as deeply ſenſible how gainfull God had made that Domeſtick duty to her own ſoul in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of her education: I ſay, being <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> what good ſhe had got by being dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently inſtructed in the principles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſhe was <hi>conſcientious</hi> in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of that duty towards thoſe whom God had committed to her truſt, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a way of exerciſing their <hi>memories</hi> in a <hi>bare verbal repetition of words,</hi> but (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to her faculty, which verily was not ordinary in her ſex) in a way of help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to underſtand the <hi>ſence</hi> and <hi>meaning;</hi> and by <hi>impreſſing</hi> upon <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:105540:31"/>what was <hi>imprinted</hi> in their <hi>meme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the abſence of her dear Husband, ſhe conſtantly <hi>performed the duty of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in her own perſon,</hi> ſave only when ſhe could call in the aſſiſtance of her own pious <hi>Paſtour,</hi> or other faithful Miniſters whom the preſent <hi>Providence</hi> had caſt into her neighbourhood, all which her Chriſtian ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging converſe had ſo marvellouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deared, that ſhe had as many <hi>Chaplains,</hi> as if ſhe had bin one of the greateſt Ladies in the Land.</p>
            <p>A true <hi>Goſpel-Sabbatarian</hi> ſhe was; and thought it no <hi>Judaiſm</hi> to keep the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Sabbath</hi> as an <hi>holy Reſt,</hi> rather en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying her <hi>body,</hi> that it ſhould have ſix dayes to her <hi>ſouls</hi> one, then ſacrilegiouſly filching out of that precious <hi>one,</hi> any parcells of time for the uſes and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the fleſh; truth is, ſhe counted e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very moment of <hi>Sabbath-time, too good</hi> for any time but <hi>Sabbath-work,</hi> unleſs it were vvhere divine indulgence had made <hi>allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> for vvorks of <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Neceſſity!</hi> In reference to both vvhich (notvvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding) ſhe vvell knevv how to <hi>ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize</hi> even <hi>them</hi> alſo into <hi>Sabbath-exerciſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:105540:31"/>
            <p>Further then theſe <hi>two,</hi> ſhe durſt not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act any of her ſervants labour: As knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Sabbath vvas the <hi>ſervants priviledge,</hi> as vvell as her ovvn. <hi>Thou and thy ſervant, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That her <hi>Servants ſouls were as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to God, as her own,</hi> and coſt Jeſus Chriſt <hi>as much blood</hi> to redeem.</p>
            <p>Therefore ſhe vvas careful that every one in her Family, ſhould not only attend the <hi>publick Ordinances;</hi> but that they ſhould improve the <hi>whole overplus</hi> of Sabbath time, in the <hi>holy exerciſes</hi> of Religion. And as God had given her an excellent faculty in <hi>taking Sermons,</hi> ſo ſhe made it her vvork conſtantly to <hi>repeat</hi> both the former and latter Sermon to her Family, vvhich ſhe did vvith ſuch a judicious accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateneſs, that the hearer could hardly miſs in the repetition, vvhat he had heard from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> at leaſt not any head or material en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largment of the Sermon.</p>
            <p>The other void ſpaces of the day ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to her Family as <hi>Gods</hi> and their <hi>own time,</hi> for divine uſes, calling upon them, to <hi>redeem it accordingly.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:105540:32"/>
            <p>You that are <hi>Governours of Families,</hi> imitate this bleſſed Saint herein alſo. The Sabbath is exceedingly fallen amongſt us, not in our <hi>Publike Aſsemblies</hi> &amp; <hi>ſtreets</hi> only, but even vvithin our private vvalls: <hi>The ſpirit of</hi> Ignatius <hi>dyed with him.</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Let every one that loves the Lord, ſanctify the Lords-day, <hi>Ignat. ep ad Magn.</hi> Hovv art thou fallen, Thou <hi>Morning-Starr?</hi> Thou Queen of days; thou <hi>golden ſpot</hi> of the week! Thou <hi>Map</hi> of Heaven! Thou <hi>birth-day</hi> of immortality! Hovv art thou fallen!</p>
            <p>You that love the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> and his <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> I charge you by all that <hi>right</hi> and <hi>intereſt</hi> you claim in either, help to lift up the head of this glorious day of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah;</hi> for the love of God do not put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvay the Pillovv from under the head of this <hi>dying day,</hi> as you vvould not be found guilty of the blood of Chriſt and of his Reſurrection; Chriſtians, ſtirr up your ſelves for the recovery of the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> of this <hi>Holy-day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. As a <hi>Friend and Neighbour:</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. As a Friend.</note> She vvas of a moſt <hi>ſweet</hi> and <hi>obliging converſe.</hi> As many <hi>loved her</hi> as <hi>knew her;</hi> as ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſhe vvas to do good offices to the <hi>poor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt,</hi> as others are to thoſe that can requite them.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:105540:32"/>
            <p>But that vvhich vvas eminent in her converſe, vvas her <hi>profitable improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of it; ſhe was not one of thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, that with the <hi>holy,</hi> could ſhew her ſelf <hi>holy;</hi> and with the <hi>prophane,</hi> could ſhew her ſelf <hi>prophane;</hi> that could talk religiouſly in one company, and <hi>vainely</hi> and <hi>frothily</hi> with others: She was not one of them that could ſhape them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into any form and garb of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Company; but ſhe was <hi>gracious</hi> and <hi>uniform</hi> in every Company, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence caſt her upon, ſpending the time in Chriſtian and profitable Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; alwayes either <hi>doing good</hi> or <hi>receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> good, (as opportunity ſerved.) But if the Company were ſuch as admitted nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; her <hi>ſilence</hi> ſhould argue her diſſent, and her withdrawment (as far as might conſiſt with civility) ſhould at once eaſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem and her ſelf of a <hi>burden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſtians, Oh that every one would herein become her <hi>followers:</hi> Oh what a deal of pretious time is waſted in idle alk, and fooliſh jeſtings, which are not convenient! how many precious hours are pent in vain and unprofitable comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hents? Yea in carnal mirth, fooliſh talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g and jeſting; which might be improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:105540:33"/>to ſpiritual, ſoul-edifying conferences; as if Chriſtians had forgotten there were ſuch a word in the Bible, <hi>Let your ſpeech be alwayes with gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce, ſeaſoned with ſalt,</hi> Col. 4.6. or that other, <hi>Redeem the time, for the dayes are evil,</hi> Eph. 5.1, 15, 16. <hi>The Lord make you wiſe to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might eaſily enlarge in theſe her <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative</hi> excellencies, but I muſt haſten.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place take a view of her in her <hi>Perſonal Capacity.</hi> And there we ſhall find theſe ſix <hi>Graces,</hi> which were eminently in her, to the obſervation of all that know her, <hi>ſc.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Holineſs, Meekneſs, Love, Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy with the afflicted people of God, Faith, Patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Her <hi>Holineſs.</hi> ſhe was a Chriſtian of a <hi>moſt unſtained Holineſs,</hi> ſhe wore the garment of her <hi>Chriſtian</hi> profeſſion without any <hi>viſible ſpot.</hi> The commo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Holineſs of the world would not ſerve he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn. <hi>Modeſty, Civility, Moral-righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> an <hi>Inoffenſive Converſation,</hi> theſe go far amongh the commonſort of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, and I wiſh many that would pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for Saints did not fall ſhort of theſe Though it is a very ſad thing, to fall <hi>ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:105540:33"/>of them</hi> that fall ſhort of <hi>Heaven; unſeſs your Righteouſneſs exceed this Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hieouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, you cannot enter, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.20</note> Bleſſed be God, the Righteouſneſs of this precious ſervant of Chriſt was of another <hi>make,</hi> a <hi>purity</hi> ſhe contended after of a <hi>peculiar ſtrain; zealous of good works;</hi> an Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that containeth all thoſe <hi>excellencies which God ſets any ſtore by;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</note> an <hi>Holineſs</hi> converſant about the whole <hi>will</hi> of God, <hi>proving what is that good, and acceptable, and perfect will of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2</note>
            </p>
            <p>She made Religion <hi>her buſineſs,</hi> Her one onely <hi>neceſſary thing:</hi> She purſued an Holineſs that comes up to its <hi>Pattern,</hi> the <hi>Pattern in the Mount:</hi> As he that called you is Holy,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.14 15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>ſo be you Holy in all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of converſation,</hi> and again, <hi>Be ye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect as your Heavenly Father is perfect.</hi> She was in all things as becometh women profeſſing the Goſpel, adorned with good works.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.10</note> And to this end with the Holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>She forgot the things that were behind, and preſſed toward the Mark, for the prize of the High-calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus. Let the ſame mind be in you</hi> (my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved) that was in this handmaid of Jeſus Chriſt; and do ye <hi>follow her, as ſhe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the bleſſed Apoſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:105540:34"/>
            <p>A Second grace wherein ſhe did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, (and indeed excell) was the grace of <hi>Meekneſs;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 12.3.</note> ſhe was of a <hi>Moſes-like</hi> ſpirit, <hi>meek</hi> to a <hi>None-ſuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She was <hi>rarely</hi> angry, <hi>never</hi> in her <hi>own Cauſe,</hi> and when in <hi>Gods,</hi> ſhe expreſt it in <hi>grief,</hi> rather then in <hi>paſſion;</hi> ſin could provoke her <hi>zeal,</hi> but not tranſport her into any undecent <hi>exceſs.</hi> In her own concerns ſhe had that abſolute domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over her own ſpirit, that as ſhe knew not how to <hi>give offence,</hi> ſo ſhe could not eaſily <hi>take any;</hi> or if any at any time were <hi>worth</hi> taking, it was ſooner <hi>forgot</hi> then <hi>acknowledged;</hi> ſhe was of ſo <hi>ſerene</hi> a temper, that an <hi>angry word</hi> was hardly ever heard from her <hi>lips;</hi> or an <hi>angry look</hi> ever ſeen in <hi>her face.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.4.</note> Oh how <hi>aimable</hi> did the <hi>ornament of a meek and quiet ſpirit</hi> render her in the eyes of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She was a rich Cabinet of heavenly Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, but ſhe knew it not; She was of as mean eſteem in her <hi>own eye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> as ſhe was honourable in the eyes of all behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.<note place="margin">Taliter pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentatae Deum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebitis A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matorem. <hi>Tert. de cul. faem.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>You that are of her Sex and Relation, Oh that you would ſtrive to <hi>imitate</hi> her in this grace alſo; beautified with this <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion;</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:105540:34"/>God, and Angels, and men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe but be in love with you</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Grace of <hi>Love</hi> was tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently in her.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Her <hi>Love to God,</hi> ſhe loved him <hi>exceedingly</hi> whom ſhe couldnot love <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Her <hi>Love to Jeſus Chriſt, who had lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſo paſſionately that he died for love of her,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>and waſhed her from her ſins in his own blood.</hi> But becauſe <hi>he loves Chriſt too little,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Minus to amat Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine qui aliquid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat quod nonpropter te amat. <hi>Aug.</hi> Pſa. <hi>45.2.</hi> Cant. <hi>3.</hi> Cant. <hi>5.10</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that loveth him for any thing but for himſelf;</hi> This precious Chriſtian lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Him not only for what <hi>he did,</hi> but for what <hi>he was;</hi> His <hi>Perſon</hi> as well as his <hi>Portion:</hi> She loved him for his <hi>Lovelineſs,</hi> as well as for his <hi>Love,</hi> ſhe looked upon <hi>Chriſt</hi> with the Spouſes eyes, <hi>fairer then the Children of men, &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>chiefeſt of ten Thouſand,</hi> The only <hi>precious one of her Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Her love to <hi>Chriſt</hi> had marvelouſly conſumed her love to the <hi>World:</hi> She was in a great degree (with the Holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) <hi>Crucified to the world,</hi> and <hi>the world to her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God had given a competent portion of the world to her, but ſhe (bleſſed be God) made it not her <hi>portion.</hi> She gave
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:105540:35"/>but very little of her <hi>Love</hi> to the vvorld; but <hi>poſſeſt</hi> the vvorld as if ſhe <hi>poſſeſt it not:</hi> In this only ſhe vvas (holily) <hi>proud,</hi> that ſhe thought her love <hi>too good</hi> for the <hi>world.</hi> Her love to Chriſt had vvonderfully vva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted and vveakned <hi>Self-love. Self</hi> vvas a very ſmall concern to her. None had leſs intereſt in her ſelf, then her ſelf.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Her Love to the <hi>Publick Aſsemblies,</hi> and <hi>Publick Ordinances;</hi> Her word was that of Holy <hi>David, Lord I have loved the habitation of thy Houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 26.8.</note> 
               <hi>and the place where thine honour dwelleth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Love to the Saints:</hi> All her delight was in them that <hi>excel in vertue.</hi> A <hi>vile perſon was contemned in her eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.2.3, 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>but ſhe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured them that fear the Lord.</hi> She choſe not her Company by their <hi>greatneſs,</hi> but by their <hi>goodneſs;</hi> a <hi>poor Saint</hi> was a more welcome gueſt to her, then a <hi>proud ſinner;</hi> ſhe loved Saints for their <hi>Sanctity;</hi> the more <hi>holy,</hi> the more her heart was knit unto them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Her love <hi>to the faithful Miniſters of the Goſpel</hi> was very eminent, <hi>the very feet of them that bring good tidings, that publiſh p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that bring good tidings of good, that publiſh ſalvation, were very beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:105540:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>in her eyes;</hi> their <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe</hi> was <hi>honourable</hi> to her above many.</p>
            <p>A fourth eminent, was Sympathy with the <hi>afflicted Churches</hi> and ſervants of Jeſus Chriſt. In all their afflictions ſhe was afflicted; her bowels were troubled for them: Yea, <hi>ſhe was in pain,</hi> like a woman in <hi>travel;</hi> who was weak, and ſhe was not weak? who was afflicted, and ſhe burnt not? ſhe was read in that <hi>Chapter of Remembrance</hi> (as one calls it) <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.3. She remembred them that are in bonds, as bound with them; and them who ſuffer adverſity, as her ſelf alſo in the made body.</p>
            <p>Surely this <hi>fellow-feeling</hi> with the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted people of God, was not more her <hi>duty</hi> then her <hi>Character;</hi> ſhe was a Chriſtian up of <hi>bowels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is verily thought, the <hi>Churches ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> was <hi>her death.</hi> Queen <hi>Mary</hi> ſaid (upon her death-bed) that if they open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her, when ſhe was dead, they would find <hi>Calais written upon her heart.</hi> If this precious Creature had been opened when ſhe was dead, you might have found <hi>Sion</hi> written upon her heart. So true a Mourner ſhe was in <hi>Sion,</hi> and for
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:105540:36"/>
               <hi>Sion,</hi> that ſhe even <hi>mourned her ſelf to death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh imitate her in this grace, all ye that <hi>love the Lord Jeſus.</hi> Behold <hi>ſhe</hi> whom your <hi>Lord loveth</hi> is <hi>ſick, ſick</hi> not of <hi>Love</hi> only but of <hi>perſecution.</hi> There is not that part of the true Church of Chriſt under heaven, upon which the <hi>hour of temptation</hi> is not in an eminent manner. The <hi>ſinners in Sion abound</hi> every where; pray ye that the number of the <hi>mourners in Sion</hi> may abound more and more. And ye that are the Lords <hi>Remembrancers,</hi> behold you have your Commiſſion, <hi>keep not ſilence</hi> and give him <hi>no reſt till he eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>and till he m ke Jeruſalem a praiſe in the Earth:</hi> How willing is God to be overcome, that bids his people wreſtle? How deſirous is God to grant, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands his ſupplicants to take no <hi>denyal</hi> at his hands, nor ſuffer him as it were to live <hi>a quiet day in Heaven,</hi> till he gives <hi>Reſt to his Church upon Earth!</hi> Improve your Commiſſion, O ye Saints of God, cry a loud, ſpare not, beg of Jeſus Chriſt, that King of Saints, hat he would bow the heavens, and come down, or ever his <hi>Sp uſe die,</hi> that he would take her up in his Arms, wipe off duſt from her face,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:105540:36"/>tears from her eyes, and blood from her wounds.</p>
            <p>Oh <hi>forget not Jeruſalem,</hi> leſt your Right-hand forget her cunning, plead hard for her, leſt your tongue cleave to the roof of your mouth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 137.5, 6.</note> Oh <hi>prefer Jeruſalem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove your chief joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. She was a woman of <hi>great Faith,</hi> the life ſhe lived in the fleſh was a <hi>life of Faith:</hi> In her <hi>natural life,</hi> in all the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick calamities</hi> of the times, <hi>and private afflictions</hi> upon her own perſon, as ſhe was a woman of much <hi>ſorrow;</hi> God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving exerciſed her with ſharp trials and afflictions in the married eſtate; Frequent <hi>Abortions, loſs of Children,</hi> and (that which muſt needs follow) a fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>diſtempered body,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay in all theſe ſhe lived by faith, and was more then Conquereſs through him that loved her: All her afflictions were but the <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als</hi> and <hi>triumph</hi> of her Faith.</p>
            <p>Faith it was that which kept her Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel ſo <hi>ſteddy</hi> in the midſt of all the Waves and Billows which fell upon her in her paſſage, that in them all ſhe was obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by all the ſtanders by, to be of an <hi>even tranquil ſpirit,</hi> not <hi>tranſported</hi> with joy in her <hi>better times,</hi> nor <hi>dejected</hi> with
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:105540:37"/>ſorrow in her worſe, but (that which was ſaid to be Queen <hi>Elizabeths Motto,</hi> was really her temper and felicity, <hi>Semper Eadem,</hi> ſhe was ſtill <hi>the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In her <hi>ſpiritual life,</hi> ſhe lived much by <hi>Faith;</hi> when ſhe could not <hi>ſee,</hi> ſhe did <hi>believe,</hi> and when in <hi>darkneſs,</hi> and had <hi>no light,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.10.</note> ſhe could <hi>truſt in the name of the Lord, and ſtay upon her God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in this did the excellency of her Faith conſiſt, <hi>ſhe durſt not believe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a promiſe,</hi> nor the <hi>promiſe</hi> without the <hi>qualification,</hi> in ſome <hi>good degree.</hi> Faith without a promiſe ſhe believed was not <hi>Faith,</hi> but <hi>Fancy;</hi> not <hi>believing,</hi> but <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming:</hi> This ſhe believed, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore never durſt <hi>believe</hi> further then ſhe had a <hi>word</hi> for it: Hence ſhe made the <hi>promiſes</hi> her dayly <hi>ſtudy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hear this all you that take up your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation <hi>upon truſt,</hi> and ſwim down the ſtream of <hi>ſecurity,</hi> not working out your ſalvation with <hi>fear and trembling;</hi> but think it enough to hope well, and to <hi>believe</hi> you do <hi>believe,</hi> &amp;c. and what will <hi>ye do in the latter end?</hi> When your <hi>Faith</hi> will prove but <hi>fancy,</hi> and your <hi>hope</hi> but as the <hi>Spiders Webb,</hi> wrought out of your own bowels, and blown away with the leaſt
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:105540:37"/>of <hi>temptation?</hi> Take heed, deceive not your ſelves with <hi>ſhadows</hi> inſtead of <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances:</hi> what good will it do you to go down to the Grave with a lie in your Right-hand; one Grain of <hi>Faith</hi> well tryed, is more worth then a pound of <hi>Faith</hi> taken up upon truſt.</p>
            <p>The ſixth and laſt Grace which I ſhall <hi>hint</hi> to you, (though herein I do both her and you wrong) is her <hi>Patience.</hi> Truly, her life and her death was nothing elſe but a Lecture of humility.</p>
            <p>I told you before, that her life (from almoſt the firſt of her married eſtate) was a life of ſuffering: Not truly, by reaſon of the leaſt <hi>unſuitableneſs</hi> in the Conjugal relation, nor meerly in regard of <hi>Abortion,</hi> and <hi>loſs of Children,</hi> both which ſhe bare with a gracious chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in ſubmiſſion to her Heavenly Father; but alſo in reſpect of an <hi>infirm Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> which ſhe carried about her; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that when the time of her diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion came, it appeared to her learned <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> that her <hi>dying ſickneſs</hi> was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a <hi>Complication of her diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> now come to the <hi>birth,</hi> which had for near <hi>Twenty years</hi> before bin <hi>breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>ripening</hi> in her tender body; which
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:105540:38"/>though they did (not ſeldom) make a viſible impreſſion upon nature; yet ſhe did carry with ſo <hi>ingenuous a diſſimulation,</hi> that her neareſt Relations could hardly diſcover any <hi>habitual diſtemper</hi> prevailing upon her, but judg'd it only ſome <hi>acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental errour</hi> in nature, eaſily capable of correction by prudent obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>But at length, thoſe ſparks which for many years lay <hi>ſmoaking</hi> and <hi>kindling within, brake out</hi> into a <hi>flame,</hi> and for near twenty weeks together by degrees, prevailed upon the Walls of her feeble Tabernacle, the anguiſh whereof, though (at times) it was beyond expreſſion full of bitterneſs and torment; yet ſhe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained it with ſuch an invincible ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of patience, as did flatter her friends into a deluſive hope, that her ſickneſs was not mortal, untill the diſſolution of nature convinced them of their too eaſie <hi>dulity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She had a <hi>peculiar patience of her own,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.19.</note> and that patience <hi>gave her the poſſeſſion of her ſoul;</hi> ſo that in her ſharpeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts with pain and ſickneſs, though (as an holy Miniſter ſaid of himſelf) ſhe might (poſſibly) <hi>groan,</hi> yet ſhe did not
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:105540:38"/>
               <hi>grumble;</hi> an impatient complaint was never heard from her lips; but if asked, how is it? Her anſwer was the Holy <hi>Martyrs word,</hi> mixt up of <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Faith;</hi> It <hi>is well,</hi> and it <hi>will be better.</hi> It <hi>is well,</hi> there was <hi>her patience,</hi> and it <hi>will be better</hi> there was her Faith: <hi>Through both</hi> which (as in the Text) <hi>She inherits the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Her Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Judgment</note>I might eaſily enlarge the <hi>Catalogue</hi> of her <hi>Vertues;</hi> ſhe was of great <hi>wiſdom</hi> and <hi>judgement,</hi> not as a <hi>Woman</hi> only, in mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging all her affairs with <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> but (much more) as a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> woman. She was not a light Sceptical profeſſour, nor one that took up her Religion upon <hi>truſt</hi> or <hi>imitation:</hi> She <hi>knew what ſhe believed,</hi> and having weighed her <hi>principles</hi> in the <hi>ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance</hi> of the <hi>Sanctuary;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.</note> and <hi>tried</hi> them by the <hi>touch-ſtone</hi> of the holy Scriptures <hi>(which from her youth ſhe had known)</hi> ſhe became rooted and grounded in the Faith,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15</note> and ſtood <hi>unmoveable</hi> and <hi>unſhaken</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the blaſts and ſtorms of <hi>ſeducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> Able not only to <hi>give an anſwer to every one that might (rationally) ask her a reaſon of the hope that was in her with meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and fear,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.</note> but as a good proficient in Chriſts School, to <hi>make an Apology</hi> for
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:105540:39"/>the truths ſhe had learned from the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Her Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety.</note>In <hi>Temperance and Sobriety,</hi> ſhe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded many, not only of the ordinary rate of vvomen, but even of ſuch as (not without cauſe) have the repute of Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel.</note>In her <hi>Habit,</hi> ſhe affected nothing of the <hi>pride and curioſity</hi> of the preſent ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration. Accounting it more honour to beautifie her <hi>Attire,</hi> then to owe any <hi>beauty</hi> to it. Nor was ſhe in love with any <hi>faſhion,</hi> but that which the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the moſt <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>modeſt</hi> of her <hi>rank</hi> commended to her.</p>
            <p>She was of great temperance <hi>in her diet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance-</note> ſhe did as much diſguſt whatever might ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor of <hi>delicacy</hi> and <hi>indulgence</hi> to the fleſh, as the delicate do what is mean and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, eating and drinking at ſuch a <hi>rate,</hi> as one whom not <hi>Nature</hi> only had <hi>dieted,</hi> but <hi>Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Provident</hi> ſhe was without <hi>avarice; fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> not that ſhe might <hi>get the more goods,</hi> but that ſhe might <hi>do the more good;</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting that het beſt <hi>riches,</hi> not which <hi>ſhe laid up for her ſelf,</hi> but that which ſhe <hi>laid out for God.</hi> Her <hi>Charity</hi> was very <hi>extenſive,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Charity.</note> not knowing any other <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits,</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:105540:39"/>but want of <hi>opportunity;</hi> nor any other <hi>partiality</hi> but the <hi>Houſhold of Faith.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Her <hi>Mercy</hi> refuſed not the loweſt <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mercy.</note> to the loweſt <hi>object;</hi> her enquiry being not what the perſon was, but what vvas the <hi>need?</hi> She thought it no robbery to impoveriſh her ſelf, that ſhe might make others rich.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Heroick ſpirit.</note>She had a <hi>tender,</hi> and yet an <hi>Heroick Spirit;</hi> ſhe feared nothing but <hi>ſin,</hi> and could bear any thing but <hi>Gods diſhonour</hi> and the <hi>reproach of Religion.</hi> A Coward ſhe was, when Chriſt (poſſibly) might ſuffer <hi>by her;</hi> but <hi>couragious,</hi> when ſhe was called to ſuffer any thing for <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Her whole deportment was made up of <hi>Sweetneſs</hi> and <hi>Gravity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gravity.</note> which put ſuch a Grace upon her, that ſhe Commenced a <hi>Matron</hi> in Religion, before her time; as if nature had over reckoned it ſelf <hi>one age</hi> of her life at leaſt, and took the degree of <hi>old age,</hi> before ſhe was forty.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Her ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity.</note>Laſtly, Her <hi>ſincerity</hi> commended her to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi> She vvas fully <hi>as much</hi> as ſhe <hi>appeared</hi> to be; to <hi>God</hi> without <hi>hipocriſie;</hi> to Man without <hi>fraud;</hi> a true <hi>Nathaniel, in whoſe ſpirit there was no guile.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:105540:40"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe Vertues,</hi> as they were eminent in her, ſo they deſerve a larger ſhare in her juſt Character; but it is time to give you ſome account of her <hi>Death;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Her Death.</note> of which though much might be ſpoken worthy ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, yet take the Epitome of it in a few words. Three things ſhe did upon her <hi>Death-Bed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>firſt thing</hi> ſhe did, was to give a <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>full account of the work of Grace</hi> wrought in her ſoul, both in the <hi>Methods</hi> and <hi>Progreſs</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>foundation</hi> whereof ſhe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged was laid in the Catechiſtical prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of her Parental education; the <hi>ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments of Religion,</hi> were by <hi>their</hi> care and <hi>her</hi> diligence, ſo diſtinctly imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in her <hi>underſtanding,</hi> that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a good <hi>foundation,</hi> upon which the <hi>ſuperſtructure</hi> of more <hi>practical</hi> and <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual truths</hi> of the Goſpel, were more <hi>proſperouſly</hi> and <hi>fruitfully raiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After that by <hi>Precept</hi> and <hi>Pattern</hi> ſhe had learned the neceſſity of <hi>ſecret duties, inſtruction</hi> and <hi>experience</hi> ſoon taught her the inſignificancy of them, without regard to the <hi>manner,</hi> as vvell as to the <hi>matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From thenceforth ſhe began ſeriouſly to ſtudy a <hi>Duty-frame of ſpirit,</hi> and to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:105540:40"/>eye the <hi>Pattern in the Mount.</hi> John 4.24.</p>
            <p>After this, notwithſtanding in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of the Miniſtry under which ſhe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved during the time of her ſingle ſtate) ſhe found her ſelf at <hi>a loſs,</hi> the Holy Ghoſt convincing her of a preſent abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and indiſpenſable need of Jeſus Chriſt in point of <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi> She well perceived her own Righteouſneſs too ſhort a garment to cover her nakedneſs from the all-piercing eye of <hi>Divine Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</hi> From thenceforth (with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) ſhe accounted all things (even the beſt of her own Righteouſneſs) but <hi>loſs and dung</hi> that ſhe might <hi>win Christ,</hi> and be found in him not having her own Righteouſneſs which is of the Law, but that which is through the Faith <hi>of Chriſt, the Righteouſneſs which is of God by Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Original Method aſſerted by our Lord, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.9, 10, 11.</note>But the Conviction ſtayed not long there, but ſoon was improved by the ſame ſpirit into a Conviction, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the <hi>beauty and excellencies</hi> that is in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> A <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhe muſt have as a fountain of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> as well as of <hi>Happineſs;</hi> for a <hi>Soveraign</hi> as well as for a <hi>Saviour,</hi> for his <hi>Perſon,</hi> as well as for
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:105540:41"/>his <hi>Portion:</hi> A Chriſt for <hi>Himſelf,</hi> as well as for <hi>Her ſelf;</hi> ſhe was <hi>ſick of Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet further, <hi>Intereſt</hi> would not ſerve her turn without <hi>evidence; Scripture evidence.</hi> This ſhe now made her buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſhe was very diligent to bring her <hi>Hopes</hi> and <hi>Evidences</hi> to the <hi>Scripture,</hi> and to <hi>compare them</hi> and <hi>the word</hi> together, by the light whereof as ſhe diſcovered any <hi>fault</hi> or <hi>defect</hi> in them or cauſe to be jealous of them; She repaired to the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious faithful Miniſters of the Goſpel, for the help of their judgement; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally that near and tender Relation, whom ſhe truſted (above any) with her ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al concerns, whom ſhe acknowledged God had made of ſingular uſe and advantage to her in the doubts and difficulties of this nature.</p>
            <p>But above all, ſhe conſtantly made her addreſs to <hi>Him,</hi> whoſe <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> is, The <hi>ſearcher of Hearts,</hi> and <hi>tryer of the Reins,</hi> with holy <hi>Davids</hi> Petition; <hi>Search me O God, and know my Heart; try me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 139.23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>and know my Thoughts: And ſee if there be any way of wickedneſs in me, and lead me in the way everlaſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From <hi>evidence</hi> at length, ſhe put in for <hi>aſſurance;</hi> in the ſerious and vigorous
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:105540:41"/>purſuit whereof, <hi>death met her,</hi> as well in the midſt of her <hi>work,</hi> as of her <hi>dayes; unexpectedly indeed,</hi> but (bleſſed be God) not <hi>unpreparedly,</hi> and though her ſickneſs was not fraught with extraordinary <hi>joyes</hi> and <hi>raviſhments:</hi> Yet ſhe was ſuſtained with a <hi>ſweet peace and ſerenity of Spirit,</hi> which God did not permit Satan to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt all her ſickneſs long; and this was not the fruit of a <hi>blind unſenſible ſecurity,</hi> (as in moſt that cry up a <hi>Lamb-like death</hi>) for <hi>ſhe was able to give anſwer to any one that asked her reaſon of the hope that was in her, with meekneſs and judgement.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It was the account ſhe her ſelf gave, why neither in her <hi>ſickneſs</hi> nor <hi>health,</hi> ſhe had experienc't any great <hi>raptures</hi> or extraordinary joyes of the <hi>Spirit of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption,</hi> as ſome do; for (ſaid ſhe) neither was <hi>I brought</hi> in with any extraordinary terrors or tremblings of the <hi>ſpirit of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage:</hi> Nevertheleſs it pleaſed the Lord not to leave <hi>Himſelf,</hi> nor his poor <hi>Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid</hi> without <hi>witneſs; not only</hi> in giving her a <hi>ſweet ſerenity</hi> of ſpirit, inſomuch that ſhe ſuffered no <hi>Ecclipſe</hi> of that <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs;</hi> (in all the time of her confinement to her Chamber) who <hi>Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> (upon the <hi>Croſs</hi>) ſuffered an Ecclipſe
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:105540:42"/>of the light of his <hi>Fathers Countenance,</hi> at what time He cried out (to the aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Heaven and Earth</hi>) <hi>My God, my God, why hast thou forſaken me?</hi> But much more, in vouchſafing her ſome immediate <hi>irradiations</hi> of his <hi>face and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,</hi> on the <hi>evening</hi> before <hi>ſhe died;</hi> at what time, a gracious intimate friend, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at a little diſtance from her Bed-ſide, forbearing to ſpeak to her, knowing her to be very much ſpent, and ſuppoſing her to be in a ſlumber; at length ſhe opened her eyes, (as if it had bin out of a ſleep) and ſeeing her friend whom ſhe loved ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by, ſhe beſpake her thus: <hi>Oh my dear friend! are you there? I have had a full anſwer of all my prayers; God hath not denyed me any of the requeſts of my ſoul, but hath fully ſatisfied my deſires.</hi> Hathe he ſo, (ſaid her friend?) Then I hope he hath heard you, <hi>in that you fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> (meaning the <hi>fear of death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">To your God and my God, to your Father &amp; my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Theſe Words ſhe often uſed</note> which formerly had held her in <hi>ſome bondage,</hi> Heb. 2.14.) <hi>She replyed,</hi> He hath, He hath; I know whom I have believed, <hi>and I am now going to him, and</hi> I ſhall ſee him <hi>(ſhortly)</hi> with theſe very eyes. <hi>You that have prayed</hi> to God for me, <hi>I deſire you would joyn with me in giving him praiſe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:105540:42"/>for this gratious anſwer of peace, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed me, poor me!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She added moreover, ſhe did not deſire prayer for the <hi>Continuance of life;</hi> but that ſhe might he reſigned <hi>up to God in prayer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.6.</note> and might be <hi>accepted in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved.</hi> And reſigned up ſhe was in a <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn manner;</hi> firſt, by ſeveral godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters then preſent; and laſt of all by that <hi>hand</hi> which by the power of the Holy Ghoſt had <hi>Midwived</hi> her into Chriſt in her <hi>Regeneration;</hi> during all which time, her ſpirit accompanied that <hi>ſolemn tranſaction,</hi> with <hi>ſtrong and vigorous affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> to the extream expence of her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ſpirits; and when all was finiſhed, being asked, whether ſhe had gone along with the Petition which had bin lifted up to God for her? She anſwered, <hi>Yes, I bleſs God I have,</hi> they were very ſweet and precious: The Lord return your kindneſs and love into your boſom a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand fold.</p>
            <p>Whereupon leaving her to try what <hi>reſt</hi> ſhe could take, being very much wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in her ſpirits; we had not bin long in our Beds ere we were call'd out in haſt to take our laſt leave of her; but her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſoul, impatient of longer diſtance
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:105540:43"/>from her Beloved, did upon [her] Lords day in the morning as early as the <hi>light</hi> might ſerve to <hi>denominate</hi> it <hi>day,</hi> take its flight to the <hi>mountains of ſpices,</hi> there to celebrate an <hi>eternal Sabbath</hi> in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom and embraces of her <hi>Heavenly-Bridegroom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Second thing ſhe did upon her <hi>Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Bed,</hi> was before the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, his Elect Angels, and thoſe Chriſtians which were about her, to make a <hi>full and clear Profeſſion of her Faith.</hi> Wherein, though ſhe took the <hi>Creed</hi> (commonly called <hi>Apoſtolical</hi>) for her <hi>Text:</hi> Yet ſhe did not content her ſelf to do it in that <hi>ſteril verbal</hi> way, of a literal repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (as the mode of moſt ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is) but upon evey <hi>Article</hi> and <hi>Clauſe,</hi> as ſhe went, enlarged her ſelf in ſo ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and ſavory a Paraphraſe of her own, as did marvelloufly affect the hearers, in ſo much that they afterward accuſed themſelves of robbery againſt their own ſouls, that they had not taken the paines to make that <hi>legible</hi> to their <hi>eyes,</hi> which ſhe had made <hi>audible</hi> to their <hi>eares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Her third and laſt dying work was, to give <hi>Counſels</hi> and <hi>Inſtructions</hi> to her <hi>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving Relations</hi> that were about her;
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:105540:43"/>which were ſo <hi>full, ſerious</hi> and <hi>ſuitable,</hi> that ſhe ſeemed (as indeed ſhe vvas) to be acted <hi>above her ſelf,</hi> her <hi>ſpiritual and Heavenly ſelf,</hi> acting the <hi>weak</hi> Organ of her <hi>body,</hi> as long as there was any paſſive capacity left in it.</p>
            <p>In a word, ſhe hath left as many Mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners behind her, as knew her, whether <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bad.</hi> The worſt in the place where ſhe lived, have given her this Teſtimony, That <hi>if ſhe be not gone to Heaven, never any went thither;</hi> which puts us to find out a new expoſition of our Lords Text, <hi>Woe unto you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.20.</note> 
               <hi>when all men ſhall ſpeak well of you, &amp;c.</hi> As for you Beloved, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Text, and make it your work to be her followers, to imitate her in her <hi>Graces</hi> and <hi>gracious Converſation,</hi> vvhoſe Faith follow, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7. It is time to conclude. But though I have given you divers <hi>Motives</hi> in the <hi>Grounds</hi> and <hi>Reaſons</hi> of the <hi>Doctrine;</hi> yet for your ſpecial <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation</hi> and <hi>encouragement,</hi> who are of her <hi>Family</hi> and dear <hi>Relations,</hi> give me leave to add ſome ſpecial <hi>Incentives</hi> and Conſiderations, to quicken you to a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous imitation of ſo excellent a Pattern.</p>
            <p>It were a fruitleſs ſorrow to go to the Sepulchre (with <hi>Mary</hi>) to <hi>weep there:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.13</note> It
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:105540:44"/>is a more profitable work, to enquire how vve may recruit our loſs; how we may expound <hi>Sampſons</hi> Riddle to <hi>get meat out of the Eater,</hi> and out of the <hi>ſtrong, ſweetneſs;</hi> hovv to make a gain of our great afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and that is the thing I would gladly preſs upon you in a fevv <hi>Motives and Conſiderations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Without a ſerious imitation of her pious example, <hi>that which was our mercy and priviledge in the enjoying of her,</hi> will turn to our <hi>ſin</hi> and the <hi>aggravation</hi> of our <hi>loſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.7. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> It is ſaid of <hi>Noah,</hi> He cocondemned the <hi>World, &amp;c.</hi> How? his <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and his <hi>Pattern,</hi> being not <hi>followed,</hi> ſhould <hi>riſe up in judgement</hi> againſt that <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> generation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 12, 21, 22.</note> and <hi>condemn them;</hi> ſo likewiſe our Lord tells the impenitent <hi>Jews</hi> that the <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>Niniveh,</hi> and the <hi>Queen of the South</hi> ſhould riſe up in judgement with that <hi>generation,</hi> and <hi>condemn them. (i.e.)</hi> The example of thoſe poor <hi>Infidels</hi> not prevailing with them, to move them to repentance, and timely and ſerious di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in the great concerments of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (having <hi>Chriſt himſelf,</hi> a greater then <hi>Jonas</hi> or <hi>Solomon</hi> to be their <hi>Preacher</hi>) ſhould in the <hi>day of judgement</hi> riſe up as a <hi>witneſs,</hi> and an aggravation of their <hi>obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate impenitency.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:105540:44"/>
            <p>Dear Sirs, We have had the light of this moſt <hi>excellent pattern,</hi> ſhining with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our Walls for diverſe years laſt paſt, (ſome of us more, ſome fewer) give me leave to tell you, even <hi>weeping,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> it leave no <hi>bettering influence</hi> upon us. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> will give in a <hi>judicial teſtimony</hi> againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the great day.</p>
            <p>She hath bin a <hi>witneſs from God to us,</hi> if (by a practical improvement of what we have ſeen divine and excellent in her) we receive not her <hi>teſtimony,</hi> ſhe will be a witneſs <hi>for God againſt us,</hi> when our Lord ſhall come to call us to an account. And O how terrible will that be! What a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful addition to our miſery; when to the <hi>loſs</hi> of ſuch a <hi>bleſſing</hi> ſhall be added the <hi>Curſe</hi> of our <hi>non-improvement of it!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Friends, it had been better never to have been <hi>Mother</hi> to ſuch a <hi>Child,</hi> never to have been <hi>Husband</hi> to ſuch a <hi>Wife,</hi> never to have been adopted to ſuch a <hi>Mother,</hi> or <hi>Servant</hi> to ſuch a <hi>Miſtris,</hi> never to have enjoyed fellowſhip with ſuch a friend; then, (when all is done) to have her come in as a <hi>witneſs againſt us,</hi> in the great day of Judgement.</p>
            <p>Oh to have bin poſſeſt of ſuch a mercy ſo many years, (as it were for no other
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:105540:45"/>end then to render our ſin the greater, and our condemnation the more grievious! that the very remembrance of her ſhould add to our torment, this will be intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable! Oh that the ſerious conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our danger, might awaken us to a fruitful contention of being like her!</p>
            <p>A Second <hi>Motive,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Motive.</hi> It will prevent a double ſin. 1 Envy.</note> This will prevent a double ſin.</p>
            <p>The firſt is that whereby we are very apt <hi>to envy the praiſes of them which are better then our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Scripture obſerves ſuch a baſeneſs in our degenerate natures,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>the ſpirit that dwelleth in us luſteth to envy.</hi> It is uſual in Scripture to call the <hi>bent</hi> and <hi>ſtrong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination</hi> of the ſoul (either to <hi>good</hi> or <hi>evil</hi>) <hi>(Spirit,)</hi> ſo it calls a <hi>worldly</hi> frame of heart <hi>the ſpirit of the world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12 <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 19.14.</note> An who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh diſpoſition the <hi>ſpirit of whoredome,</hi> frowardneſs of heart <hi>a perverſe ſpirit,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So here, a malignant diſpoſition towards others, <hi>a ſpirit luſting to envy;</hi> carrying men ſtrongly to <hi>fret,</hi> and <hi>envy</hi> at the <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> or <hi>praiſes</hi> of our brethren. We have it as ſoon as we come into the world, and it is an hard matter to kill it wholly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we die our ſelves; it is almoſt an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidemical diſeaſe: <hi>We cannot bear the praiſes of them that out-ſhine us.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:105540:45"/>
            <p>And there is <hi>pride,</hi> and <hi>ſelf-love</hi> at the bottom of it, whereby we are ready to think, that thoſe Eulogies and Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which are aſcribed to <hi>others,</hi> are due rather to <hi>our ſelves;</hi> the Laurel of praiſes would better become our Temples. Hence Saint <hi>James,</hi> having mentioned <hi>envy,</hi> ſpeaks in the verſe immediately follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of pride, as the root of that bitter fruit; <hi>God reſiſts the proud,</hi> &amp;c. Hence the <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mans</hi> queſtion is, <hi>Who am</hi> I? The <hi>proud mans</hi> queſtion is, <hi>Who am I not?</hi> Am not I as good as ſuch a one? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in am I inferiour to ſuch and ſuch? <hi>Hath the Lord indeed ſpoken only by</hi> Moſes?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 12.2.</note> 
               <hi>hath he not ſpoken alſo by us?</hi> Thus <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Mirian envyed Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Jam. <hi>4.5.</hi> Ad ſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatis ſuae non deſinit per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere, Men. Fel. Oct.</note>It is a ſin as the Text that <hi>dwelleth</hi> in the Saints, but it <hi>reigns</hi> in the wicked; the Devils proper ſin: He is an envious ſpirit, envying <hi>God</hi> his <hi>glory,</hi> and the <hi>Saints</hi> their <hi>felicity</hi> and <hi>honour;</hi> the Devil firſt envyed us the favour of God, and ever ſince we have envyed one another.</p>
            <p>Well, it is our diſeaſe: Yea, but an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>imitation</hi> of our <hi>betters,</hi> will help us to mortifie and cure it by an humble and conſcientious reflection upon our ſelves: Thus, <hi>I am ready to envy them which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:105540:46"/>in grace, but am I as careful to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate them; their graces and excellencies will carry them to heaven, but my envy may ſink me to Hell, from whence it came; while I ſhould</hi> imitate <hi>the Saints in their</hi> graces, <hi>behold I</hi> imitate the Devil, <hi>in envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe graces!</hi> Ah what will become of ſuch a wretch as I am!</p>
            <p>A ſecond ſin,<note place="margin">2 Sin. Flattery.</note> which Imitation of thoſe that excel us, will (happily) prevent, is that <hi>whereby we are prone to reſt in a ſleight commendation of their perſons.</hi> If we give them a few good words; If we can but ſay, Oh ſuch a Miniſter was an excellent <hi>Preacher,</hi> he had a <hi>rare gift</hi> in prayer, a man of admirable parts, and of ſingular piety, &amp;c. Such a man was a man of great worth and incomparable abilities! Such a woman was a woman of a meek ſpirit, one that had much communion with God, an holy woman, of large bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els and compaſſions to the afflicted Church and people of God, &amp;c. I ſay, if we can but give them a good Character, though we never contend after an holy imitation of their virtues, we think we have done enough, and there's an end.</p>
            <p>But my Beloved know we thus much.</p>
            <p>Firſt that <hi>Commendation</hi> without <hi>Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:105540:46"/>is but an <hi>unprofitable Complement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.16</note> juſt ſuch another thing as (in the matter of Charity) is as Saint <hi>James</hi> his, <hi>Be ye warmed, be ye filled,</hi> and give them nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>fire</hi> nor <hi>food,</hi> &amp;c. or like an handful of flowers ſtrewed upon the Graves of the dead, which makes the Corps ſmell never the <hi>ſweeter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Yea <hi>Commendation</hi> without <hi>Im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tation,</hi> is but our <hi>Condemnation;</hi> we condemn our ſelves of <hi>groſs hypocriſie,</hi> while we commend them; for if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>that precious,</hi> which we commend, why do we not <hi>imitate them?</hi> If we <hi>do not,</hi> why <hi>do we commend them?</hi> Thou Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite why doth thy tongue belie thy heart? or thy life contradict thy tongue? <hi>Out of thine own mouth thou ſhalt be condemned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the curing therefore of this vanity, apply we our ſelves to a ſincere and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious following of their gracious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples. If we did really believe that conformity to them were our <hi>duty,</hi> and that ſuch choice Patterns (whether of the departed, or of the <hi>ſurviving Saints</hi>) were a <hi>talent</hi> for which we muſt be reſponſable to our <hi>Lord,</hi> (as well as for the Word and Sacraments, and other helps to ſalvation) that our <hi>non-improvement of our Patterns</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:105540:47"/>as well as of our <hi>Precepts,</hi> will render us <hi>unprofitable ſervants;</hi> it would frighten us out of our torpor and ſluggiſhneſs, and make us tremble to ſatisfie our ſelves with a frigid and fruitleſs commendation of their ſhining excellencies.</p>
            <p>A Third <hi>Motive,</hi> By <hi>a faithful imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her vertues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>Motive.</hi> Imitation makes the abſent perſon, preſent.</note> 
               <hi>we may ſtill enjoy our loſt Relation.</hi> Imitation <hi>(like Faith)</hi> brings the <hi>object</hi> and the <hi>faculty</hi> together. The Limner draws not his <hi>Picture</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Perſon</hi> or the <hi>Effigies</hi> before him: Imitation makes abſent perſons to dwell together; by our imitation of our deceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Relation, we may preſerve our <hi>converſe</hi> with her, and ſhe being dead, will yet ſpeak with us; &amp; that in a more excellent manner, then while ſhe was yet in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: We may have Communion with her <hi>pure, ſpiritual, unmixt ſelf;</hi> her ſelf abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from what ever was <hi>carnal</hi> or <hi>terene</hi> in her; a communion of an higher &amp; more An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical nature &amp; advantage, then that which the beſt of Saints are capable of in this lower region; what <hi>Prelation</hi> the Apoſtle aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribeth to the Communion, which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and other Saints had with <hi>Chriſt</hi> after his <hi>Aſcention,</hi> above that which they attained, while he was with them on <hi>earth;</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:105540:47"/>namely, that whereas the converſe they had with him in the <hi>dayes of his fleſh,</hi> was but <hi>after the fleſh,</hi> in a <hi>Civil, Natural, Humane</hi> way; ſuch as <hi>poor, weak, ignorant, indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent</hi> ſervants have with a <hi>rich, powerful, wiſe</hi> bountiful Lord; (they converſt not with him in his <hi>Divine</hi> or <hi>Mediatory</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity as he came into the world to <hi>ſave ſinners;</hi> nor improved the converſe they had to <hi>heavenly uſes:</hi>) But when he vvas exalted to the Right-Hand of the Majeſty on High, they enjoyed <hi>Communion</hi> with him in a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>ſaving manner,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting the Majeſty of that <hi>State,</hi> to which he was exalted:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>Truly our Fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> with the Father <hi>by</hi> the Son, with the Son <hi>in</hi> the Father; <hi>miſterious</hi> and <hi>bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay, in ſuch a <hi>prelation</hi> (in an Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal proportion) ſtands that converſe and fellowſhip which we may enjoy with our deceaſed friend, now uncloathed and ſtript of what ever was <hi>Earthly,</hi> or <hi>ſavoured of corruption,</hi> by minding and imitating what vvas of an heavenly and divine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction in her. Yea ſuch a Communion we may have with her in our degree, (ſetting aſide what is earthly and carnal in our
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:105540:48"/>ſelves) as her ſelf now enjoyeth, with the <hi>Spirits of juſt men made perfect,</hi> with Grace,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23.</note> 
               <hi>and nothing elſe</hi> but Grace.</p>
            <p>And for this end (uſualy) God doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from us the Relations in which we took the greateſt delight and complacency, namely for the <hi>correcting of our ſenſuality;</hi> and for the awakening of us, to a more ſpiritual and heavenly improvement, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which we have with Saints on Earth, or which we may with Saints de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, in their ſeparate and heavenly ſlate. Upon this very account our Lord tells his Diſciples,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.7.</note> 
               <hi>It is expedient for you, that I go away; for if I go not away the comforter will not come; but if I go I will ſend him unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The removal of Chriſt his <hi>Corporal preſence,</hi> made vvay for his preſence in the <hi>ſpirit;</hi> many times the <hi>ſenſual</hi> and <hi>Earthy</hi> part of our deſirable Relations, ſtands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween that ſpiritual traffick we might have with them, and that heavenly fruit, vve might reap from them; in which caſe, God ſees it expedient to take them from us.</p>
            <p>My Beloved, Is there ſuch gain to be made by the loſs of our gracious friends? Is our ſpiritual life bound up in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mature death? Let us ſtudy to experience</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:105540:48"/>
            <p>It was our <hi>folly,</hi> that we did <hi>put God</hi> to exerciſe us with ſo ſharp a Diſcipline; and that may keep us from murmuring; <hi>have we not procured this unto our ſelves?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But now not to profit by this <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> will be our <hi>ſin,</hi> and the aggravation of our ſorrows. I have obſerved that there is in every <hi>affliction</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> that is before us, a <hi>bleſſing</hi> and a <hi>ſnare;</hi> a <hi>bleſſing</hi> in every <hi>affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> and a <hi>ſnare</hi> in every <hi>mercy;</hi> yea <hi>both</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>both:</hi> Now then it is worth our ſerious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>houghts, what a tremendous judgement it is, by our blindneſs and folly, to run into the <hi>ſnare,</hi> and to loſe the bleſſing; pray we for eyes to ſee the <hi>ſnare,</hi> and for grace to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void, and to diſcover the bleſſing to improve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t. <hi>Lord God</hi> (ſaid <hi>Abraham</hi>) <hi>what wilt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou give me ſeeing I go Childleſs?</hi> God had denyed him one <hi>Bleſſing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 22.16.17.</note> and he beggs of God to make him <hi>amends</hi> for it, with ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as <hi>good</hi> or <hi>better.</hi> Do we likewiſe; ſay we to him, Lord God, thou haſt taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way my <hi>Wife,</hi> my <hi>Child,</hi> my <hi>Mother,</hi> my gracious <hi>friend; what will thou give me, for her?</hi> Our friends are <hi>a Loan,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Sam. <hi>2.20. &amp; 1.28.</hi> Vis ista non ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta est Deo ſed vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menter a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta. <hi>Calv.</hi> upon <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> wrestling.</note> whom when we chearfully reſign up to God, God accounts himſelf <hi>our Debter,</hi> and he gives us leave to <hi>plead</hi> the Debt, and not to let him go untill he hath paid it; with ſuch holy incivility God is well pleaſed; let us then <hi>come with
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:105540:49"/>boldneſs to the Throne of Grace,</hi> and ſay, Lord thou haſt deprived me of my ſweet <hi>natural</hi> and <hi>evangelical</hi> ſociety with my dear Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Lord compenſate it in a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe <hi>with,</hi> and an heavenly imitation of her graces, that I may be like her in faith, in patience, in holineſs, and in every other fruit of the ſpirit, wherewith ſhe was beautified: <hi>Let a double portion of her ſpirit reſt upon me,</hi> and the debt is paid.</p>
            <p>A fourth <hi>Motive,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 <hi>Motive,</hi> It is an Antidote againſt Sorrow.</note> A ſerious imitation of her Graces, will <hi>prove a Soveraign Antidote againſt exceſſive ſorrow for her loſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a fruitleſs trouble to go to the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre to weep there with <hi>Mary</hi> and can only ſerve (if alone) to adde to our affliction; and ſurely while we do <hi>aggravate our loſs,</hi> we do alſo aggravate <hi>our ſin,</hi> and do as it were ſummon God to our Tribunal, and there ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him of <hi>Injuſtice.</hi> While we <hi>weep</hi> with <hi>Rachel, and refuſe to be comforted,</hi> we do ſullenly <hi>throw away the mercies we leave,</hi> and ſay as it were, Nay if God will not let me enjoy this mercy, <hi>let him take all:</hi> Thus we deſpiſe the mercies we enjoy. <hi>I will go down into the Grave to my Son mourning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.35.</note> ſaid old <hi>Jacob,</hi> when he thought, he had loſt his <hi>Joſeph:</hi> Sorrow makes him to ſay he knows not what; go down into the grave! and what if he did? Could he have imbraced hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:105540:49"/>
               <hi>Joſeph</hi> there? Is there any <hi>converſe</hi> in the <hi>Grave?</hi> Or do the dead comfort one another? Exceſs of ſorrow obnubilates reaſon, and maketh us <hi>loſe our ſelves</hi> after we have loſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur darlings. Oh how much better is it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o take up their graces by an holy imitation; <hi>Eliſha</hi> got more by taking up <hi>Elijahs gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent,</hi> then he would have done if he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ood ſtill, crying, <hi>My Father, My Father,</hi> &amp;c. the <hi>Mantle</hi> of the Saints graces, will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elp up to divide the <hi>waters of affliction,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e may go through them, and not be drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d with overmuch ſorrow; partly, by <hi>divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g the ſtream</hi> into another Channel, a <hi>right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hannel;</hi> a due comparing our ſelves with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ch Patterns, will diſcover to us wherein we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>defective;</hi> and ſo lead us to mourn after <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>godly manner,</hi> rather for the <hi>want</hi> of their <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>races,</hi> then for the loſs of their <hi>ſociety;</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eep out ſuch complaints, Ah how unlike <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I to my dear <hi>Wife, Child, Siſter, Friend!</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow do I fall ſhort of her <hi>meekneſs</hi> and <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ility;</hi> of her <hi>ſeriouſneſſe</hi> in <hi>Religion;</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er <hi>cloſe walking with God;</hi> of her <hi>cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith, patience,</hi> &amp;c. Oh wretch that <hi>I am!</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow ſhall I come to be like unto her? Why <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow, this is a ſorrow, that will bear its own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arges, and better our hearts! Such <hi>teares</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll ſerve to waſh off our <hi>ſpots</hi> and <hi>blemiſhes!</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſed are they, who <hi>(thus)</hi> mourn.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:105540:50"/>
            <p>And <hi>partly,</hi> our continual eying of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>excellencies,</hi> will preſent us with <hi>freſh evide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces</hi> of their <hi>glory</hi> in heavenly places. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> will ſerve (from time to time) as a perfume<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Handkercheif</hi> to wipe off tears from our eye <hi>Well, why ſhould I weep? She is</hi> happy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> loſs <hi>is her</hi> gain; <hi>while I am</hi> mourning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Earth, <hi>ſhe is</hi> triumphing <hi>in</hi> Heaven; <hi>while am</hi> weeping <hi>amongſt</hi> ſinners, <hi>ſhe is</hi> ſingi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Hallelujahs <hi>in the Celeſtial Quire of</hi> Sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>and</hi> Angels; <hi>while I lament her</hi> abſence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(having now experienced the Change)</hi> wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> not want one hour of the Communion with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>innumerable company of Angels, the general <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſembly of the firſt born which are written <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> heaven;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22 23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>and with God the Judge of all, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with Jeſus the Mediator of the new Covena<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> I ſay ſhe would not want one houres <hi>Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> in Heaven which ſhe now poſſeſſeth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>thouſand of the beſt daies that ever ſhe ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> with us in the Land of the living.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, This continual beholding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>example, will dry up the ſtream of our ſorro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> while, <hi>thereby</hi> we ſhall (in Gods way) <hi>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to our ſelves a future fellowſhip</hi> with her glory. God hath linked Grace, and Gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> together by an unſeparable connexion: that if we carefully mark every ſtep of Saints holy feet, of which they have left
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:105540:50"/>any print, and endeavour to tread exactly in them, It will infallibly bring us to <hi>their glory; what God hath joyned together all the Powers of darkneſs, ſhall never be able to put aſunder.</hi> Here is work, <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> in finite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bear its own charges, and compenſate your labour with <hi>unſpeakable reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A fifth <hi>Motive;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Motive. <hi>The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour we can do her.</hi> Ea demum est vera religio imitari quem colis Lactant.</note> An exact imitation of her eminent graces, <hi>is the greateſt honour we can lawfully put upon her.</hi> As it is our <hi>tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping</hi> of God to labour to be <hi>like him;</hi> ſo to imitate our <hi>gracious friends,</hi> is the <hi>higheſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration</hi> they are <hi>capable of;</hi> ſhould we <hi>bring Oxen and Garlands, to do ſacrifice unto her,</hi> as <hi>Jupiters</hi> Prieſts would have done to <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 14.13. Or ſhould we <hi>pray unto her and worſhip her</hi> as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts do to their Saints and Images, we pay her an honour <hi>not due,</hi> which would be a <hi>fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs</hi> piece of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> as to <hi>her, Sacrilegious</hi> as to <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>pernicious</hi> as to our <hi>own ſouls.</hi> Whereas conſcientiouſly to inſiſt in her ſteps and to ſet her up as a pattern for our <hi>religious imitation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">6. <hi>Motive.</hi> The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of our thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to God.</note> will be a laudable Teſtimony be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, that ſhe was highly <hi>honourable in</hi> our eyes; and a <hi>ſacrifice</hi> wherewith <hi>God is well pleaſed:</hi> And this hints,</p>
            <p>A Sixth <hi>Motive;</hi> Carefully to follow her pious example, is the <hi>beſt thankfulneſs we can render to God for her.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:105540:51"/>
            <p>Two things are to be done if we would be thankful; The firſt is to ſee God in thoſe graces and qualifications wherewith ſhe was beautified. To commend her for her holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, meekneſs, love to God and his Saints, fellow-feeling with Gods ſuffering people, her faith, patience, her wiſdom, temperance, prudence, mercy, &amp;c. and no more, were to magnifie <hi>Her,</hi> but to neglect <hi>God;</hi> as if ſhe had made her ſelf to differ, or had ſhined by vertue of a ſelf-born light. She was thus and thus, I, but who made <hi>her ſo?</hi> Here's our thankfulneſs to acknowledge God the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain whence all theſe ſtreams of perfection did <hi>emanare</hi> and iſſue forth; So it was with thoſe, <hi>they returned glorifying of God, who had given ſuch gifts unto men:</hi> This is right to ſee God, and to admire God in the gifts and graces of his ſervants, to look upon all the excellencies of the Saints as ſo many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections of the divine nature in them.</p>
            <p>To <hi>overlook</hi> God in the graces of the Saints, is pride and <hi>ingratitude;</hi> but to <hi>deny</hi> God, were <hi>Atheiſm.</hi> And as often as we call to mind the graces of our dear friend or friends, let us contemplate and admire the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite fulneſs that is in Jeſus Chriſt of whoſe fulneſs they received, and grace for grace, and yet in compariſon of whom, her bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was but darkneſs, and her perfections,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:105540:51"/>(pardon the word) but ſmall ſparks of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>un of Righteouſneſs, but little drops of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmenſe Ocean of divine fulneſs that dwells in Him.</p>
            <p>The ſecond expreſſion and teſtimony of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hankfulneſs after our owning of God, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cribing all the glory to God, I ſay the ſecond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing is, To write after her Copy, to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate thoſe virtues for which we would be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hankful; while we labour to be like her, <hi>we do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eally bleſs God in expreſſing the true end and deſign of divine Grace, in leaving ſuch a piece of heaven ſo long in our Cuſtody; improvement of mercies is our beſt thankfulneſs for mercies;</hi> while we do indeed <hi>make uſe of ſuch living Directories</hi> for our better <hi>glorifying of God,</hi> we do <hi>offer him praiſe;</hi> and ordering our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations aright, we ſhall (in the end) ſee the ſalvation of God.</p>
            <p>A Seventh <hi>Motive,</hi>
               <note place="margin">7. <hi>Motive.</hi> Hereby we ſhall entail Religion upon our Family.</note> A ſevere and conſtant imitation of her worthy example, will be a bleſſed expedient of <hi>entailing Religion upon our family;</hi> while each ſurviving Relation, (Oh that it might be out honour) ſhall real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endeavour in our perſons to derive down a <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctical memorial</hi> of her <hi>Piety,</hi> we ſhall keep <hi>Religion alive in the Family,</hi> and teach our poſterity how to glorifie God.</p>
            <p>Although Saints do not propagate Saints by <hi>natural Generation;</hi> yet may even the <hi>barren
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:105540:52"/>womb.</hi> and <hi>dry l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ynes,</hi> thus propagate Saints, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſpir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> Imitation</hi> of the holy lives of them tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have gone before us. Thus the <hi>Fathers to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren may make know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gods truth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.19.</note> The Grandmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Lois</hi> to the Mother <hi>Eunice,</hi> and the Mother <hi>Eunice</hi> to her <hi>Son Timothy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5.</note> propagate the Faith.</p>
            <p>Certainly <hi>holineſs</hi> may be <hi>transferred</hi> by <hi>Pattern,</hi> as well as by <hi>Precept,</hi> from one generation to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and it is not <hi>education</hi> will do it with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>example;</hi> the <hi>eye</hi> is the more creditable Inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> then the <hi>ear. Teach</hi> we our <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſo that they may <hi>ſee us:</hi> If our <hi>practice</hi> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict our <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>epts,</hi> we bid them (as it were) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lieve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s;</hi> and take the next courſe to make th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Atheists.</hi> Let us labour by both, to leave an <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Seed</hi> in our Families, of whom we may comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably ſay when we come to die, (as our Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> upon the Croſs) <hi>My ſeed ſhall ſerve him, it ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> counted to the Lord for a Generation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 22.30.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Eighthly and Laſtly, By this means (throu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> divine Grace) <hi>We ſhall provide for Death-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Comfort.</hi> As in reference to our dear Relation who is gone before us, Her <hi>Graces</hi> and <hi>graciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> life,</hi> teſtifieth comfortably concerning Her, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhe is <hi>bleſſed in her death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.23</note> 
               <hi>ſhe dyed in the Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>So</hi> our ſincere and vigorous imitation <hi>of thoſe graces,</hi> will bear a Comfortable Death-Bed Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of our <hi>future bleſſedneſs alſo. Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> to her in <hi>Grace,</hi> will (by <hi>Scripture warrant</hi>) conclude a future <hi>Conformity</hi> to her in Glory; w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being followers of her in <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Patience,</hi> (as ſhe was a follower of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and other Believer in their ſeveral generations) we ſhall together with <hi>them</hi> and <hi>her,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. Motive. <hi>4.3.</hi> Branch.</note> 
               <hi>inherit the promiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> But this hath bin already hinted, and therefor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we ſhall inſiſt on it no further.</p>
            <closer>Soli Deo Gloris.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:105540:52"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
